좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: Hello everyone, and welcome to CME
295—
Hello everyone, and welcome to CME 295--
트랜스포머 and 대규모 언어모델.
Transformers and Large Language Models.
제 이름은 Afshine입니다.
So my name is Afshine.
저는 Shervine과 함께 이 수업을 가르칠 예정입니다.
And I will be teaching this class with Shervine,
뒤쪽에 있는 분이 Shervine입니다.
who's in the back.
원문 의미: 그리고 before I start, I'm just ~할
예정입니다 introduce ourselves.
And before I start, I'm just going to introduce
ourselves.
원문 의미: 그래서 we're twin brothers, and we
actually
So we're twin brothers, and we actually
원문 의미: had a similar background.
had a similar background.
원문 의미: 그래서 we both went to a school in
France
So we both went to a school in France
원문 의미: called Centrale Paris, and then we
each went our way.
called Centrale Paris, and then we each went our
way.
원문 의미: 그래서 on my end, I went to MIT, and
then Shervine
So on my end, I went to MIT, and then Shervine
원문 의미: went to Stanford to do the ICME
Master's program.
went to Stanford to do the ICME Master's
program.
원문 의미: 그리고 after that, I guess our
industry background
And after that, I guess our industry background
원문 의미: is very similar 역시.
is very similar as well.
원문 의미: 그래서 I first went to Uber, and then
So I first went to Uber, and then
원문 의미: Shervine came to Uber 역시, and then
Shervine came to Uber as well, and then
원문 의미: Shervine left to Google, and I went
to Google.
Shervine left to Google, and I went to Google.
원문 의미: 그리고 then very recently, I joined
Netflix,
And then very recently, I joined Netflix,
원문 의미: 그리고 Shervine joined Netflix 역시.
and Shervine joined Netflix as well.
그리고 we've been working on 대규모 언어모델.
And we've been working on Large Language Models.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, I guess we have technical
backgrounds,
So yeah, I guess we have technical backgrounds,
원문 의미: 그리고 mostly oriented towards LLMs.
and mostly oriented towards LLMs.
원문 의미: OK, so why are we doing this 수업?
OK, so why are we doing this class?
원문 의미: 그래서 since 2020, Shervine and I have
been specializing in NLP.
So since 2020, Shervine and I have been
specializing in NLP.
원문 의미: 그리고 we've been giving this 수업 in
the format of a 워크숍 that
And we've been giving this class in the format
of a workshop that
원문 의미: was done on a yearly basis.
was done on a yearly basis.
원문 의미: 그래서 in 2021, 2022, 2023, 2024,
ChatGPT came in 2022,
So in 2021, 2022, 2023, 2024, ChatGPT came in
2022,
원문 의미: 그리고 suddenly there was 많은 interest
for LLMs.
and suddenly there was a lot of interest for
LLMs.
원문 의미: 그리고 so it's actually last spring
that we
And so it's actually last spring that we
원문 의미: started to offer this 수업 as a
Stanford 강좌
started to offer this class as a Stanford course
원문 의미: that is now called CME 295, and
this is the second instance.
that is now called CME 295, and this is the
second instance.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 what can you expect from this
수업?
So what can you expect from this class?
원문 의미: 그래서 first of all, LLMs are
basically everywhere now.
So first of all, LLMs are basically everywhere
now.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess our goal here is
twofold.
And I guess our goal here is twofold.
원문 의미: 그래서 the first one is to learn about
the underlying mechanism
So the first one is to learn about the
underlying mechanism
원문 의미: that makes all this work.
that makes all this work.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 see the 트랜스포머, which
And we're going to see the transformer, which
원문 의미: is the foundational 아키텍처 that makes
all this work.
is the foundational architecture that makes all
this work.
원문 의미: 그리고 then the second thing is to
know how these LLMs are 학습하다ed
And then the second thing is to know how these
LLMs are trained
원문 의미: 그리고 where they are applied.
and where they are applied.
원문 의미: 그래서 in case you're still wondering
So in case you're still wondering
원문 의미: if this 수업 is good for you, I would
if this class is good for you, I would
원문 의미: say that this 수업 is great for
people who just in general
say that this class is great for people who just
in general
원문 의미: have an interest in this field,
either because you wanted
have an interest in this field, either because
you wanted
원문 의미: to make it your career goal, if
여러분은 be a research
to make it your career goal, if you want to be a
research
원문 의미: scientist or an ML scientist, or if
여러분은 develop
scientist or an ML scientist, or if you want to
develop
원문 의미: a personal project that relies on
LLMs to some extent,
a personal project that relies on LLMs to some
extent,
원문 의미: to just knowing the caveats, I
guess what works,
to just knowing the caveats, I guess what works,
원문 의미: what doesn't, or just say if you're
in a separate field
what doesn't, or just say if you're in a
separate field
원문 의미: 그리고 you just want to know how this
whole AI, GenAI, LLMs
and you just want to know how this whole AI,
GenAI, LLMs
원문 의미: thing works and how you can apply
it to your domain.
thing works and how you can apply it to your
domain.
원문 의미: 그래서 now in terms of prerequisites,
So now in terms of prerequisites,
원문 의미: I would say that at a very minimum
I would say that at a very minimum
원문 의미: you should have some foundations in
ML,
you should have some foundations in ML,
원문 의미: like basically know how a 모델 is
학습하다ed, what
like basically know how a model is trained, what
원문 의미: a 신경망 is, and also some basics in
linear algebra,
a neural network is, and also some basics in
원문 의미: 그래서 basically how 행렬들 are
multiplied, for instance.
so basically how matrices are multiplied, for
instance.
원문 의미: 하지만 even if you have a developing,
I guess,
But even if you have a developing, I guess,
원문 의미: competency in this field, I guess
it's fine,
competency in this field, I guess it's fine,
원문 의미: we're still be here to help you
out.
we're still be here to help you out.
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess this is like the ideal
set of prerequisites.
But I guess this is like the ideal set of
prerequisites.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 still on the logistics, so this
수업 will be held every
So still on the logistics, so this class will be
held every
원문 의미: Friday from 3:30 to 5:20, and it
will be held here.
Friday from 3:30 to 5:20, and it will be held
here.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 수업 is two units.
So this class is two units.
원문 의미: 그리고 you have the choice to either
take it as a letter
And you have the choice to either take it as a
letter
원문 의미: or a credit/non-credit.
or a credit/non-credit.
원문 의미: 그래서 as you could tell from the
setup,
So as you could tell from the setup,
원문 의미: we're basically recording this 수업.
we're basically recording this class.
원문 의미: 그리고 if you cannot for some reason
attend this time,
And if you cannot for some reason attend this
time,
원문 의미: this slot, we'll make sure with
Shervine to make the recordings
this slot, we'll make sure with Shervine to make
the recordings
원문 의미: available, either tonight, like
every Friday night,
available, either tonight, like every Friday
night,
원문 의미: or on Saturday.
or on Saturday.
원문 의미: 그래서 in terms of the 성적s, so what
So in terms of the grades, so what
원문 의미: we're doing for this quarter is to
have two exams.
we're doing for this quarter is to have two
exams.
원문 의미: 그래서 one is the 중간고사, which will
So one is the midterm, which will
원문 의미: be happening during our fifth
instance, which is October 24.
be happening during our fifth instance, which is
October 24.
원문 의미: 그리고 then the second exam will be
the 기말고사,
And then the second exam will be the final exam,
원문 의미: which will be held in the week of
December 8.
which will be held in the week of December 8.
원문 의미: 그래서 date is still TBD.
So date is still TBD.
원문 의미: 그래서 we'll let you know.
So we'll let you know.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 every time we have a 강의, we'll
So every time we have a lecture, we'll
원문 의미: be posting the slides and the
recordings on the website.
be posting the slides and the recordings on the
website.
원문 의미: 그리고 in case you're interested, we
also
And in case you're interested, we also
원문 의미: have the syllabus in there, so you
have the syllabus in there, so you
원문 의미: can know a little bit what are the
topics that we'll
can know a little bit what are the topics that
we'll
원문 의미: be talking about.
be talking about.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 수업 textbook is this Super
Study Guide—
And the class textbook is this Super Study
Guide--
트랜스포머 LLMs.
Transformer LLMs.
원문 의미: 그래서 we have a copy here in case
여러분은 take a look.
So we have a copy here in case you want to take
a look.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, I guess 많은 the concepts
So yeah, I guess a lot of the concepts
원문 의미: that we have 이 수업에서 will actually
be in the book.
that we have in this class will actually be in
the book.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess it's a helpful way to
follow this 역시.
So I guess it's a helpful way to follow this as
well.
원문 의미: 그리고 also, we did some very short,
condensed version
And also, we did some very short, condensed
version
원문 의미: of this whole 수업 that we called the
VIP cheat sheet.
of this whole class that we called the VIP cheat
sheet.
원문 의미: 그래서 this one is available on GitHub
So this one is available on GitHub
원문 의미: in case you're interested.
in case you're interested.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah, we also translated it
into a number of languages now.
And yeah, we also translated it into a number of
languages now.
원문 의미: By the way, if your language is not
there, let us know,
By the way, if your language is not there, let
us know,
원문 의미: 그리고 happy to work on that 역시
together.
and happy to work on that as well together.
OK, cool.
원문 의미: I think it's the last things on the
logistics part.
I think it's the last things on the logistics
part.
원문 의미: 그래서 in terms of announcements,
we'll
So in terms of announcements, we'll
원문 의미: be posting things on Canvas.
be posting things on Canvas.
원문 의미: In case you have any questions, you
In case you have any questions, you
원문 의미: can of 강좌 reach out to us.
can of course reach out to us.
원문 의미: 하지만 there is also a tab on Canvas
that's called Ed.
But there is also a tab on Canvas that's called
Ed.
원문 의미: I'm sure you're familiar.
I'm sure you're familiar.
원문 의미: 그래서 you just click on that, just
post your question,
So you just click on that, just post your
question,
원문 의미: 그리고 then Shervine and I will be
responding.
and then Shervine and I will be responding.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess to reach out to us, you
have this mailing list.
And I guess to reach out to us, you have this
mailing list.
원문 의미: Or we're just two, so just ding us.
Or we're just two, so just ding us.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 on the logistics, do we have
any questions so far?
So on the logistics, do we have any questions so
far?
원문 의미: 그리고 one thing I forgot to mention
And one thing I forgot to mention
원문 의미: is that, given that we're recording
this 수업,
is that, given that we're recording this class,
원문 의미: I guess if you're asking a
question,
I guess if you're asking a question,
원문 의미: it may not be super clear for the
viewer what
it may not be super clear for the viewer what
원문 의미: your question was.
your question was.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 make an effort to
just repeat your question.
So I'm going to make an effort to just repeat
your question.
원문 의미: It will sound weird, but I'll try
to not forget, but yeah.
It will sound weird, but I'll try to not forget,
but yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 any questions so far on the
logistics?
So any questions so far on the logistics?
네.
Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is whether there
are coding parts in the exams.
So the question is whether there are coding
parts in the exams.
원문 의미: 그래서 the answer is no.
So the answer is no.
원문 의미: 그래서 the exams will purely focus on
concepts
So the exams will purely focus on concepts
원문 의미: that we see in 수업.
that we see in class.
원문 의미: 그리고 actually, it's not meant to
trap you.
And actually, it's not meant to trap you.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess if you follow the 수업,
if you
So I guess if you follow the class, if you
원문 의미: see the slides and the concepts
that we see, should be fine.
see the slides and the concepts that we see,
should be fine.
네.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
원문 의미: Question is, if you're waitlisted,
what do you do?
Question is, if you're waitlisted, what do you
do?
원문 의미: I think, so by experience, 많은
people
I think, so by experience, a lot of people
원문 의미: will finalize their schedule.
will finalize their schedule.
원문 의미: Some people will drop, some won't.
Some people will drop, some won't.
원문 의미: In case you're still waitlisted,
come talk to us.
In case you're still waitlisted, come talk to
us.
원문 의미: 하지만 I'm pretty confident it's going
But I'm pretty confident it's going
원문 의미: to be OK, because I think the
waitlist right now is six.
to be OK, because I think the waitlist right now
is six.
원문 의미: So, I think it should be fine.
So, I think it should be fine.
좋습니다.
Cool.
네.
Yeah.
원문 의미: They will be on the website, and
we'll
They will be on the website, and we'll
원문 의미: make sure to also post a link on
Canvas.
make sure to also post a link on Canvas.
네.
Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question was, where are the
slides.
So the question was, where are the slides.
원문 의미: 그리고 they're on the website.
And they're on the website.
Cool, yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 question is on the 가중치ing of
the exams.
So question is on the weighting of the exams.
그래서 there is no 과제.
So there is no homework.
그래서 50% is 중간고사, 50% is final.
So 50% is midterm, 50% is final.
그리고 no 성적s—
And no grades--
원문 의미: I mean, no 가중치 are from that.
I mean, no weights are from that.
원문 의미: 그리고 particular, I mean if this slot
And particular, I mean if this slot
원문 의미: is conflicting with something, just
keep in mind
is conflicting with something, just keep in mind
원문 의미: that we are recording this.
that we are recording this.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's fine if you cannot attend
this session.
So it's fine if you cannot attend this session.
네.
Yeah.
Sorry?
원문 의미: Oh, is the question that the final
Oh, is the question that the final
원문 의미: is about just the second half of
the 수업?
is about just the second half of the class?
원문 의미: We have not written the exam yet,
We have not written the exam yet,
원문 의미: 하지만 I think this is something we
are thinking of.
but I think this is something we are thinking
of.
원문 의미: 그래서 the final is probably ~할 예정입니다
be about the second half
So the final is probably going to be about the
second half
원문 의미: of the topics.
of the topics.
좋습니다.
Cool.
OK, long story short, 50% 중간고사, 50% 기말고사.
OK, long story short, 50% midterm, 50% final
exam.
그리고 it's a fun 수업.
And it's a fun class.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 with that, I'm ~할 예정입니다 just
slowly start the 수업.
So with that, I'm going to just slowly start the
class.
원문 의미: 그래서 another thing that I want to
mention
So another thing that I want to mention
원문 의미: was every time we're talking about
something,
was every time we're talking about something,
원문 의미: you will see that at the bottom of
the slide
you will see that at the bottom of the slide
원문 의미: there will be a source, and it's
mostly for— so first,
there will be a source, and it's mostly for-- so
first,
원문 의미: to credits, whatever, we're
quoting, but also
to credits, whatever, we're quoting, but also
원문 의미: for you to dig into those materials
a bit
for you to dig into those materials a bit
원문 의미: more in case you're interested.
more in case you're interested.
원문 의미: Because, of 강좌, we have only two
hours per week,
Because, of course, we have only two hours per
week,
원문 의미: 그리고 we only have nine or 10 weeks,
and we only have nine or 10 weeks,
원문 의미: 그래서 there's nowhere near enough
time for us to cover everything.
so there's nowhere near enough time for us to
cover everything.
원문 의미: 그리고 the second disclaimer is you
will see that the field is
And the second disclaimer is you will see that
the field is
원문 의미: full of abbreviations.
full of abbreviations.
원문 의미: 그래서 I myself was completely scared
of them when I started.
So I myself was completely scared of them when I
started.
원문 의미: 하지만 hopefully by the end of the 수업,
But hopefully by the end of the class,
원문 의미: you will have a mental mapping of
what
you will have a mental mapping of what
원문 의미: these abbreviations mean, respect
these abbreviations mean, respect
원문 의미: to what they correspond to.
to what they correspond to.
원문 의미: 그래서 yes, so if you have a mental
mapping
So yes, so if you have a mental mapping
원문 의미: towards the end of the 수업, then we
know e did a good job.
towards the end of the class, then we know e did
a good job.
원문 의미: 그래서 with that, let's start.
So with that, let's start.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess we will start 아주 큰 틀에서,
because I
And I guess we will start at a very high level,
원문 의미: will just assume that I guess we're
starting 처음부터.
will just assume that I guess we're starting
from scratch.
원문 의미: 그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 talk about NLP
in general.
And we're going to talk about NLP in general.
원문 의미: 그래서 NLP is ~할 예정입니다 be our first
abbreviation.
So NLP is going to be our first abbreviation.
그래서 NLP stands for 자연어 처리.
So NLP stands for Natural Language Processing.
원문 의미: 그리고 it is a field that is around
manipulating text,
And it is a field that is around manipulating
text,
원문 의미: just computing things with text.
just computing things with text.
그리고 아주 큰 틀에서, 기본적으로 분류할 수 있습니다 NLP tasks
And at a very high level, can basically classify
NLP tasks
원문 의미: into three buckets.
into three buckets.
원문 의미: 그래서 the first bucket is what we
call 분류.
So the first bucket is what we call
classification.
그래서 we have an 입력 텍스트 as an 입력.
So we have an input text as an input.
원문 의미: 그리고 then what we want is to predict
something.
And then what we want is to predict something.
원문 의미: 그래서 one 예시 is you have a movie
review
So one example is you have a movie review
원문 의미: 그리고 여러분은 predict whether the
sentiment is positive,
and you want to predict whether the sentiment is
positive,
원문 의미: negative, or neutral.
negative, or neutral.
그래서 that's one 예시.
So that's one example.
원문 의미: You can also have 의도 탐지, just
knowing
You can also have intent detection, just knowing
원문 의미: what, for instance, the person
wants to do.
what, for instance, the person wants to do.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you say, I want
to create an alarm for tomorrow.
So let's suppose you say, I want to create an
alarm for tomorrow.
원문 의미: 그래서 the intent here is create an
alarm.
So the intent here is create an alarm.
원문 의미: 그래서 also to detect a language— so
for instance,
So also to detect a language-- so for instance,
원문 의미: if you write among French, you want
if you write among French, you want
원문 의미: to detect that text is in French,
topic 모델ing.
to detect that text is in French, topic
modeling.
원문 의미: The second category is what we call
multi-분류.
The second category is what we call
multi-classification.
원문 의미: 그래서 we still have a text as 입력,
So we still have a text as input,
원문 의미: 하지만 this time we predict more than
one thing.
but this time we predict more than one thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have a number of tasks in
that bucket 역시.
So you have a number of tasks in that bucket as
well.
원문 의미: 그래서 one that is very popular is
called 개체명 인식,
So one that is very popular is called Named
Entity Recognition,
a.k.a.
NER.
원문 의미: 그래서 what that task does is, given
an 입력 텍스트,
So what that task does is, given an input text,
원문 의미: 우리는 basically label some specific
words, like,
we want to basically label some specific words,
like,
원문 의미: for instance, identifying whether
something
for instance, identifying whether something
원문 의미: is a location, or a time, and so
on.
is a location, or a time, and so on.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have some other tasks
역시
And then you have some other tasks as well
원문 의미: that are a little bit more on the
linguistic side.
that are a little bit more on the linguistic
side.
원문 의미: I think they're less trendy now,
but I
I think they're less trendy now, but I
원문 의미: guess 10 years ago it was something
guess 10 years ago it was something
원문 의미: that people would study a lot.
that people would study a lot.
원문 의미: 그래서 part of speech tagging, which
is about just figuring out which
So part of speech tagging, which is about just
figuring out which
원문 의미: word is a noun, a verb, et cetera,
word is a noun, a verb, et cetera,
원문 의미: or some parsing-related tasks, so
dependency or constituency
or some parsing-related tasks, so dependency or
constituency
parsing.
원문 의미: 그리고 then the last bucket, which is
very popular these days is
And then the last bucket, which is very popular
these days is
the 생성 bucket.
the generation bucket.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have the text as 입력, and
you also
So you have the text as input, and you also
have text as 출력.
have text as output.
원문 의미: 그리고 here the length can be
variable,
And here the length can be variable,
원문 의미: meaning you don't know what the
length of your 출력 text
meaning you don't know what the length of your
output text
원문 의미: will be beforehand.
will be beforehand.
원문 의미: 그래서 here you have several tasks.
So here you have several tasks.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, you have 기계번역.
So for instance, you have machine translation.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, something in
English and I
So for instance, something in English and I
원문 의미: wanted to let's say German.
wanted to let's say German.
원문 의미: 질의응답— so typically
Question answering-- so typically
원문 의미: the ChatGPT, Gemini that you're
using, the assistant.
the ChatGPT, Gemini that you're using, the
assistant.
원문 의미: 그래서 you ask a question and you have
a response.
So you ask a question and you have a response.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have other tasks 역시,
like 요약,
And then you have other tasks as well, like
summarization,
원문 의미: 여러분은 summarize an article, let's
say,
you want to summarize an article, let's say,
원문 의미: or just generate something.
or just generate something.
원문 의미: 그래서 something can be generate
codes, generate a poem,
So something can be generate codes, generate a
poem,
원문 의미: can also be 많은 things.
can also be a lot of things.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 now what we will do is go
through these tasks one by one
So now what we will do is go through these tasks
one by one
원문 의미: to just illustrate what people
typically handle with.
to just illustrate what people typically handle
with.
원문 의미: 그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 start with the
first bucket, which
So we're going to start with the first bucket,
which
원문 의미: is the 분류 bucket.
is the classification bucket.
그리고 here we're ~할 예정입니다 illustrate
And here we're going to illustrate
원문 의미: this with the 감성 추출 task.
this with the sentiment extraction task.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we have a
sentence,
So let's suppose we have a sentence,
원문 의미: "this teddy bear is so cute."
"this teddy bear is so cute."
원문 의미: We want our 모델 to predict this to
be a positive sentiment.
We want our model to predict this to be a
positive sentiment.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically what you would use is
sentiment
So typically what you would use is sentiment
원문 의미: extraction data sets.
extraction data sets.
원문 의미: 그래서 I mentioned movie reviews, so
this is IMDb critiques.
So I mentioned movie reviews, so this is IMDb
critiques.
원문 의미: 하지만 you also have reviews about
products,
But you also have reviews about products,
원문 의미: 그래서 Amazon reviews or tweets.
so Amazon reviews or tweets.
원문 의미: 이제 I guess it's called X, so X
posts.
Now I guess it's called X, so X posts.
원문 의미: 그리고 the way you would evaluate such
출력s
And the way you would evaluate such outputs
원문 의미: would be by typically using
traditional 분류
would be by typically using traditional
classification
metrics.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have accuracy, which is
what
So you have accuracy, which is what
원문 의미: is the percentage of the
observations
is the percentage of the observations
원문 의미: that you correctly predicted.
that you correctly predicted.
원문 의미: 하지만 you also have two 키 metrics,
But you also have two key metrics,
원문 의미: which I'm just ~할 예정입니다 remind.
which I'm just going to remind.
원문 의미: I'm not sure if everyone knows
about them.
I'm not sure if everyone knows about them.
원문 의미: 그래서 one is precision, which is, 중에서
all
So one is precision, which is, out of all
원문 의미: the positive predictions that you
made,
the positive predictions that you made,
원문 의미: which ones were correct?
which ones were correct?
원문 의미: 그리고 then the second one is recall.
And then the second one is recall.
원문 의미: 중에서 all the true labels, how many
of them
Out of all the true labels, how many of them
원문 의미: did you correctly predict as being
positive?
did you correctly predict as being positive?
원문 의미: 그리고 you have this metric called the
F1 score, which
And you have this metric called the F1 score,
which
원문 의미: basically takes the harmonic mean
of precision
basically takes the harmonic mean of precision
원문 의미: 그리고 recall to just give you one
number.
and recall to just give you one number.
원문 의미: 그래서 now you may wonder, why do you
need all these metrics?
So now you may wonder, why do you need all these
metrics?
원문 의미: 그래서 the short answer is that
sometimes you have tasks
So the short answer is that sometimes you have
tasks
원문 의미: 그리고 data sets where your 수업es are
very imbalanced.
and data sets where your classes are very
imbalanced.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, you can have 99%
of your data set
So for instance, you can have 99% of your data
set
원문 의미: that is a positive label, and then
only 1% of the data
that is a positive label, and then only 1% of
the data
원문 의미: set which is negative.
set which is negative.
원문 의미: 그리고 so here if you take a metric
like accuracy,
And so here if you take a metric like accuracy,
원문 의미: can be very misleading.
can be very misleading.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 if you have a 모델 that would
predict everything
Because if you have a model that would predict
everything
원문 의미: as the majority 수업, then you will
have a great 수업ifier,
as the majority class, then you will have a
great classifier,
원문 의미: 하지만 that's not the case.
but that's not the case.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's why precision and recall
really play a role.
So that's why precision and recall really play a
role.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's for the first one.
So that's for the first one.
원문 의미: 그래서 now let's move to the second
category of NLP tasks.
So now let's move to the second category of NLP
tasks.
원문 의미: 그래서 this one is the multi-분류
category.
So this one is the multi-classification
원문 의미: 그래서 you have an 입력 텍스트 and you
predict multiple things.
So you have an input text and you predict
multiple things.
원문 의미: 그리고 we're illustrating this with
the NER task, which
And we're illustrating this with the NER task,
which
원문 의미: as I mentioned is about identifying
as I mentioned is about identifying
원문 의미: the category of given words.
the category of given words.
원문 의미: 그리고 so here, for instance, 우리는
identify a teddy bear
And so here, for instance, we want to identify a
teddy bear
원문 의미: as being an entity.
as being an entity.
원문 의미: I guess for that, you would use 분류
metrics, but not
I guess for that, you would use classification
원문 의미: at the sentence level, but more
either at the 토큰 level
at the sentence level, but more either at the
token level
원문 의미: or at the entity-type level.
or at the entity-type level.
원문 의미: 그리고 by that I mean, let's suppose
you have a category,
And by that I mean, let's suppose you have a
category,
원문 의미: let's say location.
let's say location.
그리고 여러분은 know how well you're predicting
And you want to know how well you're predicting
원문 의미: words in that category.
words in that category.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would typically aggregate
these metrics
So you would typically aggregate these metrics
원문 의미: as a function of that.
as a function of that.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: OK, let's go to the last category,
which
OK, let's go to the last category, which
원문 의미: is, as I mentioned, the most
popular one.
is, as I mentioned, the most popular one.
원문 의미: 그래서 this one is text in, text out.
So this one is text in, text out.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm illustrating this with the
기계번역
So I'm illustrating this with the machine
translation
원문 의미: task, which is around translating a
text from a source
task, which is around translating a text from a
source
원문 의미: language to a target language.
language to a target language.
원문 의미: 그래서 here you have the 예시 with
English to French.
So here you have the example with English to
French.
원문 의미: 그래서 cute teddy bear is reading, un
ours en peluche mignon lit.
So cute teddy bear is reading, un ours en
peluche mignon lit.
원문 의미: 그래서 for that, I guess it's harder
to get data sets,
So for that, I guess it's harder to get data
sets,
왜냐하면 here 여러분은 have pairs of texts.
because here you need to have pairs of texts.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have a very popular data
set
So you have a very popular data set
원문 의미: that's called WMT, which stands for
워크숍 on Machine
that's called WMT, which stands for Workshop on
Machine
원문 의미: Translation.
Translation.
원문 의미: 그리고 that one contains a bunch of
paired 시퀀스s
And that one contains a bunch of paired
sequences
원문 의미: in different languages.
in different languages.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, you have the
English-French, English-German,
So for instance, you have the English-French,
English-German,
원문 의미: coming from the European Parliament
data set,
coming from the European Parliament data set,
원문 의미: for instance.
for instance.
원문 의미: 그래서 to evaluate those, to evaluate
So to evaluate those, to evaluate
원문 의미: the performance of your 모델, it's
actually a lot more tricky.
the performance of your model, it's actually a
lot more tricky.
원문 의미: Because, as you can imagine, you
can have many different ways
Because, as you can imagine, you can have many
different ways
원문 의미: to translate something.
to translate something.
원문 의미: I'm sure many of us in the room are
bilingual, trilingual.
I'm sure many of us in the room are bilingual,
trilingual.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's what is making it this
hard.
So that's what is making it this hard.
원문 의미: 그래서 in the past, people have used
several rule-based metrics
So in the past, people have used several
rule-based metrics
to do that.
원문 의미: 그래서 one that you may have heard is
BLEU.
So one that you may have heard is BLEU.
원문 의미: BLEU stands for Bilingual
Evaluation Under Study.
BLEU stands for Bilingual Evaluation Under
Study.
원문 의미: 그리고 it is a measure of how well
your translation stands
And it is a measure of how well your translation
stands
원문 의미: with respect to a reference text.
with respect to a reference text.
원문 의미: Same story for ROUGE, which is
actually a suite of metrics,
Same story for ROUGE, which is actually a suite
of metrics,
원문 의미: 하지만 captures that in a different
way.
but captures that in a different way.
원문 의미: 그리고 you will see that the 머신러닝
community
And you will see that the machine learning
원문 의미: is funny, because BLEU—
is funny, because BLEU--
원문 의미: I'm not sure if you know French—
means blue,
I'm not sure if you know French-- means blue,
원문 의미: 하지만 rouge means red.
but rouge means red.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess they tried to add some
fun in this.
So I guess they tried to add some fun in this.
원문 의미: 하지만 the problem with these metrics
But the problem with these metrics
원문 의미: is that you always need a reference
text.
is that you always need a reference text.
원문 의미: 그래서 you basically need labels.
So you basically need labels.
원문 의미: 그리고 in practice, having labels is
very cost expensive.
And in practice, having labels is very cost
expensive.
원문 의미: It takes 많은 time, 많은 money to get
labels.
It takes a lot of time, a lot of money to get
그리고 우리가 볼 것입니다 later in the 수업
And we will see later in the class
원문 의미: that with the progress that we have
made in the LLM space,
that with the progress that we have made in the
LLM space,
원문 의미: or that the community has made in
the LLM space,
or that the community has made in the LLM space,
원문 의미: we can actually forego of this
reference-based metrics
we can actually forego of this reference-based
metrics
원문 의미: 그리고 go towards a more
reference-free metrics.
and go towards a more reference-free metrics.
그리고 우리가 볼 것입니다 that later on.
And we will see that later on.
원문 의미: 그리고 then the last metric that I
will say that people sometimes
And then the last metric that I will say that
people sometimes
원문 의미: use is called perplexity.
use is called perplexity.
원문 의미: 그리고 perplexity only looks at the
probabilities
And perplexity only looks at the probabilities
원문 의미: that are 출력 by the 모델.
that are output by the model.
원문 의미: 그리고 it basically quantifies how
surprised
And it basically quantifies how surprised
the 모델 is by its 출력.
the model is by its output.
원문 의미: 그래서 BLEU and ROUGE, the higher the
better.
So BLEU and ROUGE, the higher the better.
원문 의미: Perplexity, the lower the better.
Perplexity, the lower the better.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess LLMs have been a hot
topic since 2022.
And I guess LLMs have been a hot topic since
2022.
원문 의미: 하지만 actually, the field goes way
back, way before that year.
But actually, the field goes way back, way
before that year.
원문 의미: 그래서 in the '80s, we'll see it in a
second,
So in the '80s, we'll see it in a second,
원문 의미: 하지만 there's a 수업 of 모델 that were
actually thought
but there's a class of models that were actually
thought
원문 의미: of, even in the '80s.
of, even in the '80s.
원문 의미: 그리고 the '90s, we had LSTM that
we'll see also in a second.
And the '90s, we had LSTMs that we'll see also
in a second.
원문 의미: 하지만 the problem was, during that
time,
But the problem was, during that time,
원문 의미: we didn't have the internet.
we didn't have the internet.
원문 의미: We didn't have 많은 compute.
We didn't have a lot of compute.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess this was 그중 하나의
limiting factors which
And I guess this was one of the limiting factors
which
원문 의미: prevented the 모델 from today from
being 학습하다ed.
prevented the models from today from being
trained.
원문 의미: 그리고 then more recently, we've had
several advances.
And then more recently, we've had several
advances.
원문 의미: 그래서 Word2vec was really 그중 하나의
pioneering work
So Word2vec was really one of the pioneering
work
원문 의미: in just computing meaningful 임베딩.
in just computing meaningful embeddings.
원문 의미: 그리고 we'll see it in a second.
And we'll see it in a second.
그리고 then, of 강좌, we had the 트랜스포머,
And then, of course, we had the transformers,
원문 의미: which were part of a paper that was
published in 2017, which
which were part of a paper that was published in
2017, which
원문 의미: is basically at the foundation of
모든 모델
is basically at the foundation of all of the
models
원문 의미: that you see today.
that you see today.
원문 의미: 그리고 then these 모델, they just were
scaled up, both by compute,
And then these models, they just were scaled up,
both by compute,
원문 의미: 하지만 also in terms of the data that
was used to 학습하다 them.
but also in terms of the data that was used to
train them.
원문 의미: 그리고 that's how LLMs were dubbed.
And that's how LLMs were dubbed.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess these are more like the
2020s.
And I guess these are more like the 2020s.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, I guess we'll see those.
But yeah, I guess we'll see those.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: Any questions on, I guess, the 큰 틀?
Any questions on, I guess, the high level?
다들 괜찮나요?
Everyone good?
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess the first question that
I
So I guess the first question that I
원문 의미: want to ask ourselves is, what 우리는
do
want to ask ourselves is, what we want to do
원문 의미: is to have a 모델 that handles text.
is to have a model that handles text.
원문 의미: 하지만 모델, they understand numbers,
But models, they understand numbers,
원문 의미: they don't really understand text.
they don't really understand text.
원문 의미: 그래서 우리는 somehow do something with
that text
So we need to somehow do something with that
text
원문 의미: to make it more quantifiable,
something
to make it more quantifiable, something
원문 의미: that a 모델 can understand.
that a model can understand.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you look at a sentence, for
instance,
So if you look at a sentence, for instance,
원문 의미: "a cute teddy bear is reading," you
first need to ask yourself,
"a cute teddy bear is reading," you first need
to ask yourself,
원문 의미: how can you cut this sentence to
pass it to a 모델?
how can you cut this sentence to pass it to a
model?
원문 의미: 그래서 this part is called 토큰화.
So this part is called tokenization.
원문 의미: 그리고 what that entails is basically
And what that entails is basically
원문 의미: cutting the text with respect to
some arbitrary unit of text.
cutting the text with respect to some arbitrary
unit of text.
원문 의미: 그래서 there are several ways of doing
this.
So there are several ways of doing this.
원문 의미: I guess the first way is doing it
completely arbitrarily.
I guess the first way is doing it completely
arbitrarily.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, for instance, you would
have "a."
So here, for instance, you would have "a."
원문 의미: That would be one unit of text.
That would be one unit of text.
원문 의미: "Cute" could be another unit of
text.
"Cute" could be another unit of text.
원문 의미: "Teddy bear" would be another one,
and so on.
"Teddy bear" would be another one, and so on.
원문 의미: 그리고 by the way, the unit of text is
And by the way, the unit of text is
원문 의미: called a 토큰, which is why the
method is called 토큰화.
called a token, which is why the method is
called tokenization.
원문 의미: Another way would be to just
separate by words.
Another way would be to just separate by words.
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess we would have always
pros and cons.
But I guess we would have always pros and cons.
I guess 그중 하나의 goals that 우리는 achieve
I guess one of the goals that we want to achieve
원문 의미: is for us to then be able to
represent these 토큰
is for us to then be able to represent these
tokens
원문 의미: in a meaningful way.
in a meaningful way.
원문 의미: 그래서 one con with doing this at the
word level
So one con with doing this at the word level
원문 의미: is you will end up with words that
look similar,
is you will end up with words that look similar,
원문 의미: 하지만 that are actually considered as
different 토큰.
but that are actually considered as different
tokens.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess the limitation here is
And I guess the limitation here is
원문 의미: you will need to compute 임베딩
you will need to compute embeddings
원문 의미: for these similar yet different 토큰
for these similar yet different tokens
원문 의미: 그리고 somehow make their 임베딩 similar.
and somehow make their embeddings similar.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'll give you an 예시.
So I'll give you an example.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose I have the word
"bear."
So let's suppose I have the word "bear."
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have another word,
plural form "bears."
And then you have another word, plural form
"bears."
원문 의미: 그래서 these two words, they are very
similar.
So these two words, they are very similar.
원문 의미: Just one is singular, the other one
is plural.
Just one is singular, the other one is plural.
원문 의미: If we go ahead with the word-level
토큰화,
If we go ahead with the word-level tokenization,
원문 의미: 그러면 we will end up with just two
different entities,
then we will end up with just two different
entities,
원문 의미: which are basically just considered
as different.
which are basically just considered as
different.
원문 의미: Same with "run," and then "runs,"
variations of verbs.
Same with "run," and then "runs," variations of
verbs.
원문 의미: 그래서 for that reason, people have
dug
So for that reason, people have dug
원문 의미: into a category of 토크나이저s that
into a category of tokenizers that
원문 의미: are called subword 토크나이저s, which is
around leveraging roots
are called subword tokenizers, which is around
leveraging roots
원문 의미: of words in order to find what are
the common roots that we
of words in order to find what are the common
roots that we
원문 의미: can find in these words.
can find in these words.
원문 의미: So, for instance, for bear and
bears,
So, for instance, for bear and bears,
원문 의미: you would have the bear particle
that would be shared.
you would have the bear particle that would be
shared.
원문 의미: 그리고 so I guess the pro is that you
get to leverage
And so I guess the pro is that you get to
leverage
원문 의미: the root of the words.
the root of the words.
원문 의미: 하지만 then the con here is that your
시퀀스 would be longer.
But then the con here is that your sequence
would be longer.
그리고 우리가 볼 것입니다 why this is a con.
And we will see why this is a con.
원문 의미: I guess later on, I guess I can
give you a preview.
I guess later on, I guess I can give you a
preview.
원문 의미: 그래서 the complexity of these 모델
So the complexity of these models
원문 의미: is also a function of the 시퀀스
length.
is also a function of the sequence length.
그래서 the more 토큰 여러분은 process,
So the more tokens you have to process,
원문 의미: the more time it will take for your
모델 to run,
the more time it will take for your model to
run,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 it needs to basically process
all these 토큰.
because it needs to basically process all these
tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's one con.
So that's one con.
원문 의미: 그래서 pro is it leverages the root of
words.
So pro is it leverages the root of words.
원문 의미: Con is it just makes your 시퀀스s
longer.
Con is it just makes your sequences longer.
원문 의미: You have a last category of ways of
토큰izing things, which
You have a last category of ways of tokenizing
things, which
원문 의미: is just going at the character
level,
is just going at the character level,
원문 의미: just like taking out characters.
just like taking out characters.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, I guess, you and I when
we write a message,
So here, I guess, you and I when we write a
message,
원문 의미: we typically have sometimes
misspellings.
we typically have sometimes misspellings.
원문 의미: 그리고 with the subword way of 토큰izing
things,
And with the subword way of tokenizing things,
원문 의미: you may not be able to recognize
the word that
you may not be able to recognize the word that
원문 의미: has been misspelled.
has been misspelled.
원문 의미: 그리고 this is something that the
character-level 토크나이저
And this is something that the character-level
tokenizer
원문 의미: can, I guess, take into
consideration.
can, I guess, take into consideration.
원문 의미: 하지만 here the problem is you have a
시퀀스 length that's
But here the problem is you have a sequence
length that's
원문 의미: much, much longer, which will make
your 모델,
much, much longer, which will make your model,
원문 의미: I guess, take much more time to
process the 시퀀스.
I guess, take much more time to process the
sequence.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's one con.
So that's one con.
원문 의미: 그리고 then the other con is, I guess,
And then the other con is, I guess,
when 여러분은 represent each of these 토큰,
when you want to represent each of these tokens,
원문 의미: I guess it's very hard to know that
a representation
I guess it's very hard to know that a
representation
원문 의미: of a letter really means.
of a letter really means.
원문 의미: Like, what does the representation
of the letter U
Like, what does the representation of the letter
U
mean.
원문 의미: It's very hard.
It's very hard.
OK, cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 I have just a quick recap.
So I have just a quick recap.
원문 의미: 그래서 word-level is a super naive
way, super simple way of,
So word-level is a super naive way, super simple
way of,
원문 의미: I guess, dividing your text into
arbitrary units.
I guess, dividing your text into arbitrary
units.
원문 의미: 하지만 then the problem is, as we
mentioned,
But then the problem is, as we mentioned,
원문 의미: we do not leverage the root of
words.
we do not leverage the root of words.
원문 의미: 그리고 I did not mention this, but
there is a term.
And I did not mention this, but there is a term.
원문 의미: Whenever you cut something and then
at inference time
Whenever you cut something and then at inference
time
when 여러분은 make a prediction,
when you want to make a prediction,
원문 의미: I guess, one prerequisite that you
have is
I guess, one prerequisite that you have is
원문 의미: that 여러분은 have the 토큰 that you saw
at 학습 time,
that you need to have the token that you saw at
training time,
여러분은 have it in your 학습 sets.
you need to have it in your training sets.
원문 의미: 그리고 the problem is, let's suppose
at inference time
And the problem is, let's suppose at inference
time
원문 의미: you cut your text into words.
you cut your text into words.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's suppose you have not seen
a word at 학습 time.
And let's suppose you have not seen a word at
training time.
원문 의미: You will need to mark it as
unknown.
You will need to mark it as unknown.
원문 의미: 그리고 so this thing is called OOV,
중에서 Vocabulary.
And so this thing is called OOV, Out Of
Vocabulary.
원문 의미: 그래서 luckily, the subword-level
토크나이저
So luckily, the subword-level tokenizer
원문 의미: mitigates that problem.
mitigates that problem.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have a lower risk of OOV,
but still you can have.
So you have a lower risk of OOV, but still you
can have.
원문 의미: 그리고 as we mentioned, in terms of
the pro,
And as we mentioned, in terms of the pro,
원문 의미: you leverage the roots of the
words.
you leverage the roots of the words.
원문 의미: 그리고 then character-level, it's
robust to our misspellings
And then character-level, it's robust to our
misspellings
원문 의미: 그리고 our casing errors.
and our casing errors.
원문 의미: 하지만 the problem is it makes
computations just much slower.
But the problem is it makes computations just
much slower.
원문 의미: 그리고 your 시퀀스s would be very, very
long,
And your sequences would be very, very long,
원문 의미: which will also make your, I guess,
which will also make your, I guess,
원문 의미: inference time much higher.
inference time much higher.
원문 의미: That sound good?
That sound good?
원문 의미: I guess this is really the
foundation, I guess,
I guess this is really the foundation, I guess,
원문 의미: how to handle things with text.
how to handle things with text.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, does that 말이 됩니다 overall?
But yeah, does that make sense overall?
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: OK, so now what we did is we took
an 입력 텍스트.
OK, so now what we did is we took an input text.
원문 의미: What we did is we cut it into parts
that are basically 토큰.
What we did is we cut it into parts that are
basically tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서 in order for our 모델 to
understand these 토큰,
So in order for our model to understand these
tokens,
우리는 find a representation 각각에 대해 of them.
we need to find a representation for each of
them.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, we're ~할 예정입니다 take a
look at this.
So here, we're going to take a look at this.
그래서 that's called a 단어 표현.
So that's called a word representation.
원문 의미: Or I guess, in a more correct way,
Or I guess, in a more correct way,
원문 의미: it should be 토큰 representation.
it should be token representation.
원문 의미: 그래서 우리는 find a way to represent
each of these 토큰.
So we want to find a way to represent each of
these tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서 the simple and naive way to do
this
So the simple and naive way to do this
원문 의미: would be to just assign the one hot
벡터 각각에 대해 word
would be to just assign the one hot vector for
each word
or 각각에 대해 토큰.
or for each token.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, let's suppose we
have
So for instance, let's suppose we have
원문 의미: a vocabulary of three 토큰—
a vocabulary of three tokens--
원문 의미: book, soft, and teddy bears.
book, soft, and teddy bears.
원문 의미: We would have, let's say, soft.
We would have, let's say, soft.
That is 1, 0, 0 벡터.
That is 1, 0, 0 vector.
원문 의미: Teddy bear, that is, let's say a 0,
1, 0 벡터.
Teddy bear, that is, let's say a 0, 1, 0 vector.
원문 의미: 그리고 book, that is, let's say, a 0,
0, 1 벡터.
And book, that is, let's say, a 0, 0, 1 vector.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is called a One-Hot
Encoding, OHE.
So this is called a One-Hot Encoding, OHE.
원문 의미: We'll typically see.
We'll typically see.
그래서 cool.
So cool.
원문 의미: This is a way to represent our 토큰.
This is a way to represent our tokens.
원문 의미: 하지만 basically what people want to
do
But basically what people want to do
원문 의미: is compare these 토큰 to basically
see
is compare these tokens to basically see
원문 의미: which ones are more similar to what
other ones.
which ones are more similar to what other ones.
원문 의미: 그래서 common similarity measure that
people use
So common similarity measure that people use
원문 의미: is something called cosine
similarity.
is something called cosine similarity.
원문 의미: I'm not sure if you have heard of
it.
I'm not sure if you have heard of it.
그래서 생각할 수 있습니다 of it as just seeing
So you can think of it as just seeing
원문 의미: what angle these 벡터 make in the n
차원al space.
what angle these vectors make in the n
dimensional space.
원문 의미: 그리고 if, I guess, they are pointing
in the same direction,
And if, I guess, they are pointing in the same
direction,
원문 의미: 그러면 maybe they're similar.
then maybe they're similar.
원문 의미: Maybe if they're orthogonal, maybe
they're independent.
Maybe if they're orthogonal, maybe they're
independent.
원문 의미: 그리고 if they're completely opposite,
then
And if they're completely opposite, then
원문 의미: maybe they're opposite.
maybe they're opposite.
원문 의미: That's basically the mental 모델 우리는
go into.
That's basically the mental model we want to go
into.
원문 의미: 그래서 the problem is, if you
represent your 토큰 in a one
So the problem is, if you represent your tokens
in a one
원문 의미: hot fashion, you will end up with
all your 벡터
hot fashion, you will end up with all your
vectors
원문 의미: being orthogonal to one another.
being orthogonal to one another.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's the problem.
So that's the problem.
원문 의미: 그래서 ideally, what we want is for 토큰
So ideally, what we want is for tokens
원문 의미: that mean the same or similar to
basically have
that mean the same or similar to basically have
원문 의미: a high similarity.
a high similarity.
원문 의미: 그리고 for 토큰 that are not similar on
about
And for tokens that are not similar on about
원문 의미: different thing, to be more
orthogonal.
different thing, to be more orthogonal.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, just for illustrative
purposes, teddy bears are soft.
So here, just for illustrative purposes, teddy
bears are soft.
원문 의미: 그래서 you want teddy bear and soft to
be, I guess,
So you want teddy bear and soft to be, I guess,
원문 의미: with a high similarity.
with a high similarity.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's say teddy bear and book,
which is independent,
And let's say teddy bear and book, which is
independent,
원문 의미: you want them to be closer to 0.
you want them to be closer to 0.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's what you want.
So that's what you want.
원문 의미: That's what you have with one-hot
encoding,
That's what you have with one-hot encoding,
원문 의미: 그리고 that's what you want.
and that's what you want.
네.
Yeah.
Sorry?
Oh, I see.
원문 의미: The question is, why do you care
about the norm?
The question is, why do you care about the norm?
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess cosine similarity is
actually normalized by norms.
So I guess cosine similarity is actually
normalized by norms.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's dot products.
So it's dot products.
원문 의미: Oh, you mean why did I just put dot
product here instead of 2?
Oh, you mean why did I just put dot product here
instead of 2?
Oh, I see.
원문 의미: 그리고 your question is, why do we not
care about the norm?
And your question is, why do we not care about
the norm?
원문 의미: Cool, I guess the viewers know the
question.
Cool, I guess the viewers know the question.
원문 의미: I guess these measures, they are
all measures.
I guess these measures, they are all measures.
원문 의미: They are all ways to try to capture
these similarity things.
They are all ways to try to capture these
similarity things.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess why do you not care
about the norm?
So I guess why do you not care about the norm?
원문 의미: I guess it's how people have tried
to quantify that.
I guess it's how people have tried to quantify
that.
원문 의미: I guess you will need to see how
your 벡터 are 학습하다ed
I guess you will need to see how your vectors
are trained
원문 의미: 그리고 whether the norm would be
indicative of something.
and whether the norm would be indicative of
something.
원문 의미: I guess the best answer I can give
you is, I guess,
I guess the best answer I can give you is, I
guess,
원문 의미: this is a measure.
this is a measure.
원문 의미: This is not the perfect measure.
This is not the perfect measure.
원문 의미: People may use also dot product as
a measure,
People may use also dot product as a measure,
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, I don't have a great
answer for you.
but yeah, I don't have a great answer for you.
원문 의미: 하지만 as long as you capture, I
guess,
But as long as you capture, I guess,
원문 의미: how these 벡터 they're pointing,
how these vectors they're pointing,
원문 의미: I guess, typically what you care
about is the angle between them.
I guess, typically what you care about is the
angle between them.
원문 의미: 하지만 typically, you don't really
take
But typically, you don't really take
원문 의미: into consideration the norm.
into consideration the norm.
원문 의미: Cool, any questions?
Cool, any questions?
다른 질문 있나요?
Any other questions?
원문 의미: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
원문 의미: It's a great question.
It's a great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is around size of
vocabulary
So the question is around size of vocabulary
원문 의미: 그리고 how that would inform the
choice with respect
and how that would inform the choice with
respect
원문 의미: to word, subword, and how that
changes across languages.
to word, subword, and how that changes across
languages.
원문 의미: 그래서 great question.
So great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 I would say it really depends,
first
So I would say it really depends, first
원문 의미: of all, on the tasks that you're
trying to achieve.
of all, on the tasks that you're trying to
achieve.
원문 의미: If your task is just about one
language,
If your task is just about one language,
원문 의미: you will just take that same
language.
you will just take that same language.
원문 의미: You would typically go with a
subword 토크나이저 just because
You would typically go with a subword tokenizer
just because
원문 의미: of the reasons that we mentioned
here.
of the reasons that we mentioned here.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess subwords is a nice
trade-off between being
So I guess subwords is a nice trade-off between
being
원문 의미: able to identify words by their
roots,
able to identify words by their roots,
원문 의미: like leveraging that, but also
running less into the OOV risk.
like leveraging that, but also running less into
the OOV risk.
원문 의미: 그래서 in terms of the size, I know
that people
So in terms of the size, I know that people
원문 의미: have tried different things.
have tried different things.
원문 의미: I think typically for English, you
I think typically for English, you
원문 의미: would target something on the order
of tens of thousands
would target something on the order of tens of
thousands
원문 의미: of vocabulary size.
of vocabulary size.
원문 의미: 하지만 nowadays, the 모델, they are
multilingual,
But nowadays, the models, they are multilingual,
원문 의미: they are also about codes.
they are also about codes.
원문 의미: 그래서 you will see that the
vocabulary size now
So you will see that the vocabulary size now
원문 의미: is sometimes on the order of
hundreds of thousands.
is sometimes on the order of hundreds of
thousands.
원문 의미: 그래서 with respect to Chinese, so I
guess
So with respect to Chinese, so I guess
원문 의미: you have this difference in
characters that you're using.
you have this difference in characters that
you're using.
원문 의미: 그래서 for Latin, I guess it's the
alphabet
So for Latin, I guess it's the alphabet
원문 의미: we're all accustomed to.
we're all accustomed to.
원문 의미: 하지만 of 강좌 for the other ones,
But of course for the other ones,
원문 의미: you'd have something similar, but
in I
you'd have something similar, but in I
원문 의미: guess the target language
character.
guess the target language character.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, I would say order of
magnitude, tens of thousands
So yeah, I would say order of magnitude, tens of
thousands
원문 의미: for one language, hundreds of
thousands if it's multilingual.
for one language, hundreds of thousands if it's
multilingual.
원문 의미: These are the order of magnitude
that 여러분은 target for.
These are the order of magnitude that you want
to target for.
Cool, yeah.
원문 의미: Great question.
Great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is, how do you get
those 임베딩?
So the question is, how do you get those
embeddings?
원문 의미: 그래서 it's actually the next slide.
So it's actually the next slide.
그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 talk about this.
So I'm going to talk about this.
Cool, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 now that we know that the
one-hot encoding is not
So now that we know that the one-hot encoding is
not
원문 의미: a good way to represent 토큰, what
우리는 do
a good way to represent tokens, what we want to
do
원문 의미: is to learn those 임베딩 from the
data.
is to learn those embeddings from the data.
원문 의미: 그래서 I mentioned that there was this
paper that came out
So I mentioned that there was this paper that
came out
원문 의미: in the 2010s— so I think it was
2013— that was called Word2vec.
in the 2010s-- so I think it was 2013-- that was
called Word2vec.
원문 의미: 그리고 the reason why it was so
popular
And the reason why it was so popular
원문 의미: is because they showed a very
intuitive and interpretable way
is because they showed a very intuitive and
interpretable way
원문 의미: of seeing these 임베딩, because they
were saying
of seeing these embeddings, because they were
saying
원문 의미: something like, OK, king is to
queen, what this is to that,
something like, OK, king is to queen, what this
is to that,
원문 의미: like Paris is to France what Berlin
is to Germany.
like Paris is to France what Berlin is to
Germany.
원문 의미: 그래서 there was basically a way to 말이
됩니다 of the 임베딩.
So there was basically a way to make sense of
the embeddings.
원문 의미: 그래서 now the question is, how did
they do that?
So now the question is, how did they do that?
원문 의미: 그래서 they had two ways of computing
these 임베딩.
So they had two ways of computing these
embeddings.
원문 의미: 그래서 one way was called continuous
bag of words.
So one way was called continuous bag of words.
원문 의미: The other one was called skip gram.
The other one was called skip gram.
원문 의미: 하지만 they all rely on the same idea,
But they all rely on the same idea,
원문 의미: which is let's just leverage texts
that we have, and then try
which is let's just leverage texts that we have,
and then try
원문 의미: to predict something that is 일부
text,
to predict something that is part of the text,
원문 의미: based on, let's say, the 문맥.
based on, let's say, the context.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, continuous bag of
words, the goal
So for instance, continuous bag of words, the
goal
원문 의미: is you take into consideration the
words that are
is you take into consideration the words that
are
원문 의미: around a given target words.
around a given target words.
원문 의미: 그리고 your goal is to predict that
target word.
And your goal is to predict that target word.
원문 의미: 그리고 skip gram is the opposite.
And skip gram is the opposite.
원문 의미: You go from a target word and you
You go from a target word and you
원문 의미: want to predict the words that are
around it.
want to predict the words that are around it.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess this task is commonly
called a proxy task.
So I guess this task is commonly called a proxy
task.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 at the end of the day, in this
exercise,
Because at the end of the day, in this exercise,
원문 의미: what we care about is not
necessarily
what we care about is not necessarily
원문 의미: to predict the next word, or at
least not yet.
to predict the next word, or at least not yet.
원문 의미: Our goal is to learn a
representation of these words
Our goal is to learn a representation of these
words
원문 의미: that are meaningful.
that are meaningful.
원문 의미: 그리고 so here the idea is, if you
have a 모델 that somehow knows
And so here the idea is, if you have a model
that somehow knows
원문 의미: how to predict, let's say, the next
word, then it
how to predict, let's say, the next word, then
it
원문 의미: means that your 모델 has some
understanding of how language
means that your model has some understanding of
how language
원문 의미: works, which is basically what you
want.
works, which is basically what you want.
원문 의미: You basically want an 임베딩 that is
reflective
You basically want an embedding that is
원문 의미: of, I guess, what language is,
which is king and queen,
of, I guess, what language is, which is king and
queen,
원문 의미: or similar, Paris and France, this
is a capital.
or similar, Paris and France, this is a capital.
원문 의미: 여러분은 have these associations
embedded
You want to have these associations embedded
원문 의미: in the representation.
in the representation.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's go through a very simple
예시
And let's go through a very simple example
원문 의미: of what that looks like.
of what that looks like.
원문 의미: 그래서 here in our 예시, let's suppose
that our proxy task is
So here in our example, let's suppose that our
proxy task is
원문 의미: about predicting the next word.
about predicting the next word.
원문 의미: 그래서 here what we take is a very
vanilla neural
So here what we take is a very vanilla neural
원문 의미: network 모델, which basically
receives a 벡터 of size v,
network model, which basically receives a vector
of size v,
원문 의미: has multiplication and a 바이어스 term
has multiplication and a bias term
원문 의미: to get a hidden state, and then
another set of multiplications
to get a hidden state, and then another set of
multiplications
원문 의미: to get our final 벡터.
to get our final vector.
원문 의미: 그래서 here it's basically a very
simple 신경망.
So here it's basically a very simple neural
network.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 입력 is of size v. The hidden
layer is of size
So the input is of size v. The hidden layer is
of size
원문 의미: d, which is typically much smaller
than the vocabulary.
d, which is typically much smaller than the
vocabulary.
원문 의미: 그래서 vocabulary is typically like
tens of thousands
So vocabulary is typically like tens of
thousands
원문 의미: or hundreds of thousands.
or hundreds of thousands.
원문 의미: 그래서 d is typically hundred.
So d is typically hundred.
원문 의미: Like, 768, for instance, is one 예시
of 차원.
Like, 768, for instance, is one example of
dimension.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's much, much smaller.
So it's much, much smaller.
원문 의미: 그래서 what we're trying to do is to
learn the 단어 표현
So what we're trying to do is to learn the word
representation
원문 의미: through this proxy task.
through this proxy task.
그리고 what we're ~할 예정입니다 do is try
And what we're going to do is try
원문 의미: to consider the words as 입력s and
predict the next word.
to consider the words as inputs and predict the
next word.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's go with the first word of
the 시퀀스.
So let's go with the first word of the sequence.
원문 의미: 그래서 by the way, I use 토큰 and words
interchangeably.
So by the way, I use token and words
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we have the word
"a," and 우리는 predict
So let's suppose we have the word "a," and we
want to predict
원문 의미: the next word, which is the word
"cute."
the next word, which is the word "cute."
원문 의미: 그래서 what we do is we take the word
"a," we take the one-hot
So what we do is we take the word "a," we take
the one-hot
원문 의미: encoding representation, and we
pass it through the network.
encoding representation, and we pass it through
the network.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, if you're familiar with
신경망,
So here, if you're familiar with neural
networks,
원문 의미: 그래서 here you have, I guess, a
multiplication
so here you have, I guess, a multiplication
원문 의미: between a 행렬 and this 벡터.
between a matrix and this vector.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have a hidden state
representation,
So you have a hidden state representation,
원문 의미: which is a 벡터 of size d.
which is a vector of size d.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, let's suppose it's 0.2
and 0.9, so D equal 2.
So here, let's suppose it's 0.2 and 0.9, so D
equal 2.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have, I guess, another
pass here.
And then you have, I guess, another pass here.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you get, after 소프트맥스, a
set
And then you get, after softmax, a set
원문 의미: of probabilities which are around
of probabilities which are around
원문 의미: seeing what is the next word.
seeing what is the next word.
원문 의미: 그래서 in this 예시, we have a
vocabulary of size 6.
So in this example, we have a vocabulary of size
6.
원문 의미: 그래서 the first word is predicted
with 확률
So the first word is predicted with probability
원문 의미: 0.2, second word, 0.4, and then the
other words
0.2, second word, 0.4, and then the other words
원문 의미: are all 0.1 in this 예시.
are all 0.1 in this example.
그래서 let's suppose that 우리는 somehow
So let's suppose that we want to somehow
원문 의미: be able to maximize our prediction
be able to maximize our prediction
원문 의미: to be the second word of the
vocabulary, which is the 0.4.
to be the second word of the vocabulary, which
is the 0.4.
원문 의미: 그래서 we basically compare the
prediction with, I guess,
So we basically compare the prediction with, I
guess,
원문 의미: 0, 1, 0, 0, 0, which is the
representation
0, 1, 0, 0, 0, which is the representation
원문 의미: of the second word of the
vocabulary.
of the second word of the vocabulary.
원문 의미: 그리고 then we do the back prop, we
update the 가중치.
And then we do the back prop, we update the
weights.
원문 의미: I'm not sure if everyone is
familiar with that part.
I'm not sure if everyone is familiar with that
part.
원문 의미: 하지만 the idea here is, once you
obtain a prediction,
But the idea here is, once you obtain a
prediction,
원문 의미: you compute the loss, so typically
cross-entropy,
you compute the loss, so typically
원문 의미: which will determine how far off
you are from the true answer.
which will determine how far off you are from
the true answer.
원문 의미: 그리고 based on that difference,
you're
And based on that difference, you're
~할 예정입니다 update the 가중치 in order
going to update the weights in order
원문 의미: to make your prediction closer to
the truth.
to make your prediction closer to the truth.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's what you do.
So that's what you do.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you repeat that process.
And then you repeat that process.
원문 의미: Let's suppose you take the word
"cute," which, as we said,
Let's suppose you take the word "cute," which,
as we said,
원문 의미: is the second word in the
vocabulary.
is the second word in the vocabulary.
원문 의미: 그래서 the one-hot encoding
representation is 0, 1, 0, 0, 0.
So the one-hot encoding representation is 0, 1,
0, 0, 0.
원문 의미: 그래서 you go through that network,
you have a hidden state,
So you go through that network, you have a
hidden state,
원문 의미: like the 벡터 is 0.8 and 0.4.
like the vector is 0.8 and 0.4.
원문 의미: You do that again.
You do that again.
그리고 what 여러분은 do is to predict the next
토큰,
And what you want to do is to predict the next
token,
원문 의미: 그리고 here is teddy bear.
and here is teddy bear.
원문 의미: 그리고 so you see now your 모델 in this
예시
And so you see now your model in this example
원문 의미: is predicting the next word to be
uniform,
is predicting the next word to be uniform,
하지만 여러분은 somehow maximize the 확률 for teddy
bear.
but you want to somehow maximize the probability
for teddy bear.
원문 의미: 그래서 you go about doing this again
and again for all the words.
So you go about doing this again and again for
all the words.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the end of the day, you
obtain a 모델
And at the end of the day, you obtain a model
원문 의미: that learns how to predict the next
word, which is basically
that learns how to predict the next word, which
is basically
원문 의미: the proxy task.
the proxy task.
원문 의미: 그리고 what you're ~할 예정입니다 do is to
take the representation
And what you're going to do is to take the
representation
원문 의미: that the 모델 learns, which is the
green units.
that the model learns, which is the green units.
원문 의미: 그래서 what happens now is every time
you have a word,
So what happens now is every time you have a
word,
원문 의미: you just represent that as a
one-hot encoding representation.
you just represent that as a one-hot encoding
representation.
원문 의미: 그리고 you just multiply this with
these 가중치,
And you just multiply this with these weights,
원문 의미: 그리고 then you obtain the green
representation.
and then you obtain the green representation.
그리고 that is your 단어 표현.
And that is your word representation.
이해되나요?
Does that make sense?
Yeah, yeah.
원문 의미: Yeah, great question, great
question.
Yeah, great question, great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is about what does
v correspond to
So the question is about what does v correspond
to
원문 의미: 그리고 why there's only six.
and why there's only six.
원문 의미: 그래서 yes, in this 예시 we only have
six possible words, which
So yes, in this example we only have six
possible words, which
원문 의미: is basically the vocabulary size,
just like a very toy
is basically the vocabulary size, just like a
very toy
원문 의미: 예시, because in practice there is
many more.
example, because in practice there is many more.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess that's 그중 하나의
challenges with language.
So I guess that's one of the challenges with
language.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can technically have many
variations
So you can technically have many variations
원문 의미: of words, which is why if you take
a word-level way
of words, which is why if you take a word-level
way
원문 의미: to divide your text into 토큰, you
can end up
to divide your text into tokens, you can end up
원문 의미: with the vocabulary that's very
big,
with the vocabulary that's very big,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 여러분은 account for all the
variations of given
because you need to account for all the
words.
원문 의미: 그리고 the other thing that I want to
point out
And the other thing that I want to point out
원문 의미: is, let's suppose you have a
vocabulary size of 6,
is, let's suppose you have a vocabulary size of
6,
원문 의미: 그리고 it's the six words that you saw
at 학습 time.
and it's the six words that you saw at training
time.
원문 의미: 하지만 what happens if at inference
time
But what happens if at inference time
원문 의미: you have a word that you have not
seen at 학습 time?
you have a word that you have not seen at
training time?
원문 의미: 그리고 so the answer for that is
typically what people do
And so the answer for that is typically what
people do
원문 의미: is they reserve a spot for what
they
is they reserve a spot for what they
원문 의미: call an unknown 토큰 or
out-of-vocabulary 토큰,
call an unknown token or out-of-vocabulary
token,
원문 의미: which is basically 생각할 수 있습니다 of it
as a bucket 모든 것에 대해thing
which is basically you can think of it as a
bucket for everything
원문 의미: that we were not able to identify.
that we were not able to identify.
원문 의미: 그래서 if let's suppose at inference
time
So if let's suppose at inference time
원문 의미: you have a 토큰 that you were not
able to identify,
you have a token that you were not able to
identify,
원문 의미: they will all take that
representation,
they will all take that representation,
원문 의미: which is the unknown 토큰
representation.
which is the unknown token representation.
원문 의미: 그리고 this is, by the way, something
And this is, by the way, something
원문 의미: that I guess the word-level 토크나이저
has trouble to do,
that I guess the word-level tokenizer has
trouble to do,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you will have a much bigger
chance of having
because you will have a much bigger chance of
having
원문 의미: out-of-vocabulary 토큰.
out-of-vocabulary tokens.
원문 의미: Subword level will have a lower
chance.
Subword level will have a lower chance.
원문 의미: 그리고 then character level, I guess,
And then character level, I guess,
원문 의미: you don't have that problem.
you don't have that problem.
원문 의미: Does that answer your question?
Does that answer your question?
네.
Yeah.
Cool, yeah.
원문 의미: Great, great question.
Great, great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 first question is, when you're
done?
So first question is, when you're done?
원문 의미: 그래서 the thing with the proxy task
is when you 학습하다 your 모델,
So the thing with the proxy task is when you
train your model,
원문 의미: I guess your true objective is to
not really learn—
I guess your true objective is to not really
learn--
원문 의미: I mean, in this case—
I mean, in this case--
원문 의미: to learn how to predict the next
word.
to learn how to predict the next word.
원문 의미: Your objective is to have
meaningful representations.
Your objective is to have meaningful
representations.
원문 의미: 하지만 what you can do is to somehow
track
But what you can do is to somehow track
원문 의미: the 손실함수 for the proxy task that
you're pursuing,
the loss function for the proxy task that you're
pursuing,
원문 의미: 하지만 then also taking into
consideration that this is not
but then also taking into consideration that
this is not
원문 의미: necessarily your end goal.
necessarily your end goal.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess one very reasonable way
So I guess one very reasonable way
원문 의미: of going about doing this is just
to wait until your 모델
of going about doing this is just to wait until
your model
converges.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, what you do is you track
the loss
So here, what you do is you track the loss
원문 의미: as a function of—
as a function of--
원문 의미: 그래서 there's this term "epoch," just
how many times your 모델
so there's this term "epoch," just how many
times your model
sees the 학습 set.
sees the training set.
원문 의미: 그리고 so you compare these different
curves.
And so you compare these different curves.
원문 의미: 그리고 when this converges, this is
typically a good time
And when this converges, this is typically a
good time
원문 의미: to stop the 학습 process and just see
if that makes sense.
to stop the training process and just see if
that makes sense.
원문 의미: Depends on your downstream task, of
강좌.
Depends on your downstream task, of course.
하지만 that's one.
But that's one.
원문 의미: 그래서 your second question— sorry,
can you
So your second question-- sorry, can you
원문 의미: repeat the second question?
repeat the second question?
원문 의미: Yeah, yeah, oh, great question.
Yeah, yeah, oh, great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is, how do you
know when the 생성 stops?
So the question is, how do you know when the
generation stops?
원문 의미: I guess, otherwise it will never
stop.
I guess, otherwise it will never stop.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, exactly.
So yeah, exactly.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have some special 토큰.
So you have some special tokens.
일반적으로 you have end of 시퀀스, end of 시퀀스.
Typically, you have end of sequence, end of
sequence.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically when you have the end
of 시퀀스 토큰 generated,
So typically when you have the end of sequence
token generated,
원문 의미: 그러면 it's when it stops.
then it's when it stops.
All right.
원문 의미: 그래서 second question was what
informs
So second question was what informs
원문 의미: the size of the hidden layer?
the size of the hidden layer?
원문 의미: I would say it's a trade-off,
because you
I would say it's a trade-off, because you
원문 의미: want the 임베딩 to be rich enough
want the embedding to be rich enough
원문 의미: that it can be informative for your
downstream task.
that it can be informative for your downstream
task.
그래서 for instance, if 여러분은 somehow get
So for instance, if you want to somehow get
원문 의미: an 임베딩 of, let's say, your
sentence,
an embedding of, let's say, your sentence,
그리고 if 여러분은 ~하고자 합니다, let's say, do a
very, very
and if you want to, let's say, do a very, very
원문 의미: specialized task, like with 많은
different outcomes,
specialized task, like with a lot of different
outcomes,
원문 의미: maybe you want a 벡터 that recaptures
that, so maybe you
maybe you want a vector that recaptures that, so
maybe you
원문 의미: want a bigger 벡터, but if you had a
very simple task,
want a bigger vector, but if you had a very
simple task,
원문 의미: maybe a smaller 벡터 might 말이 됩니다.
maybe a smaller vector might make sense.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess the size of your hidden
차원
So I guess the size of your hidden dimension
원문 의미: also impacts the complexity of
whatever you're running after.
also impacts the complexity of whatever you're
running after.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 of 강좌, if you have longer 벡터,
Because of course, if you have longer vectors,
원문 의미: you'll have more computation, so
your inference will be probably
you'll have more computation, so your inference
will be probably
원문 의미: more expensive, et cetera.
more expensive, et cetera.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess there's 많은 factors.
So I guess there's a lot of factors.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess just to recap, one is
how complicated
So I guess just to recap, one is how complicated
원문 의미: your downstream task is.
your downstream task is.
원문 의미: Second one is how sensitive are you
Second one is how sensitive are you
원문 의미: with latency, cost, all these
things.
with latency, cost, all these things.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's really a trade-off.
So it's really a trade-off.
원문 의미: 하지만 out there you would typically
But out there you would typically
원문 의미: see 임베딩 of a pool of hundreds or
thousands.
see embeddings of a pool of hundreds or
원문 의미: 물론 these 모델, they've been growing,
Of course, these models, they've been growing,
원문 의미: 그래서 this number may change.
so this number may change.
원문 의미: 하지만 that's the order of magnitude
But that's the order of magnitude
원문 의미: that you're looking at.
that you're looking at.
Right.
원문 의미: This is indeed empirical.
This is indeed empirical.
Yeah, yeah.
원문 의미: I guess you can also rely on what
others found
I guess you can also rely on what others found
원문 의미: 그리고 just go from that.
and just go from that.
원문 의미: 하지만 768, these numbers are things
that people typically
But 768, these numbers are things that people
typically
take.
Cool, yeah.
원문 의미: Great question.
Great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is, how can you
distinguish
So the question is, how can you distinguish
원문 의미: words that are spelled the same but
in different 문맥s?
words that are spelled the same but in different
contexts?
원문 의미: 그래서 you're way ahead of me.
So you're way ahead of me.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is basically the basics.
So this is basically the basics.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 tackle methods
And we're going to tackle methods
원문 의미: that can tackle these problems of
just 문맥ualizing
that can tackle these problems of just
contextualizing
원문 의미: the word in the sentence.
the word in the sentence.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, so we'll see that in a
bit.
So yeah, so we'll see that in a bit.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: I'm not on time.
I'm not on time.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'll try to get moving.
So I'll try to get moving.
원문 의미: 그래서 OK, so now what we did was see
So OK, so now what we did was see
원문 의미: how we could learn representations
of 토큰.
how we could learn representations of tokens.
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess you may also want to
get representations
But I guess you may also want to get
representations
원문 의미: of sentences or pieces of text.
of sentences or pieces of text.
원문 의미: 그래서 one very naive way to do that
with what 우리가 보았습니다 before
So one very naive way to do that with what we
saw before
원문 의미: is to take something like the
average of words,
is to take something like the average of words,
원문 의미: let's say, the 단어 표현s.
let's say, the word representations.
원문 의미: 하지만 the problem is you lose 많은
meaning,
But the problem is you lose a lot of meaning,
원문 의미: you lose the order, you lose—
you lose the order, you lose--
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess here, I think you
pointed out very well,
and I guess here, I think you pointed out very
well,
원문 의미: the representations that you learn
the representations that you learn
원문 의미: are 토큰-specific, regardless of
where they're at.
are token-specific, regardless of where they're
at.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's why we have a 수업 of 모델
So that's why we have a class of models
원문 의미: that aim at capturing the
sequential nature of how
that aim at capturing the sequential nature of
how
원문 의미: text appears.
text appears.
원문 의미: 그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 talk about RNN,
which stands
So we're going to talk about RNNs, which stands
원문 의미: for Recurrent 신경망.
for Recurrent Neural Network.
원문 의미: 그래서 what RNN do is, instead of
processing words
So what RNNs do is, instead of processing words
원문 의미: one at a time, what they do is they
one at a time, what they do is they
원문 의미: keep a hidden representation of the
sentence so far,
keep a hidden representation of the sentence so
far,
원문 의미: 그리고 they consider 토큰 one at a time.
and they consider tokens one at a time.
원문 의미: 그래서 as I mentioned before, this
technique was actually
So as I mentioned before, this technique was
actually
원문 의미: introduced a fair amount of time
ago, so in the '80s.
introduced a fair amount of time ago, so in the
'80s.
원문 의미: 그리고 what this 모델 does is it takes
into consideration
And what this model does is it takes into
consideration
원문 의미: the order at which words appeared
or 토큰 appeared.
the order at which words appeared or tokens
appeared.
원문 의미: 그리고 so in this 예시, you start the,
And so in this example, you start the,
원문 의미: I guess, processing at the very
beginning of the sentence.
I guess, processing at the very beginning of the
sentence.
원문 의미: You have some dummy hidden states
that is called A,
You have some dummy hidden states that is called
A,
원문 의미: typically denoted A or H. It's
called
typically denoted A or H. It's called
원문 의미: the hidden state, activation, or
even sometimes a 문맥 벡터.
the hidden state, activation, or even sometimes
a context vector.
원문 의미: 그리고 you have some 일종의 a module that
And you have some kind of a module that
원문 의미: takes into account the hidden state
so far
takes into account the hidden state so far
원문 의미: 그리고 the word at time step t, so
here time step 1.
and the word at time step t, so here time step
1.
원문 의미: 그래서 here what it does is it takes
in the meaning of the sentence
So here what it does is it takes in the meaning
of the sentence
원문 의미: 그래서 far and takes into
consideration
so far and takes into consideration
원문 의미: the word that is happening now.
the word that is happening now.
원문 의미: 그리고 it produces an 출력 벡터 that
And it produces an output vector that
원문 의미: here can be used to try to predict
the next word.
here can be used to try to predict the next
word.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance here we have this
hidden state
So for instance here we have this hidden state
원문 의미: 그리고 the representation of the word
and the representation of the word
원문 의미: that then you have some 행렬
multiplications
that then you have some matrix multiplications
원문 의미: in this blue box.
in this blue box.
원문 의미: 그리고 you have an 출력 벡터 that you
And you have an output vector that you
원문 의미: try to 학습하다 on predicting the next
words.
try to train on predicting the next words.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you keep on doing that by
keeping
And then you keep on doing that by keeping
원문 의미: track of these hidden states.
track of these hidden states.
원문 의미: 그리고 so you repeat the process.
And so you repeat the process.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess the way you would
interpret these hidden states
And I guess the way you would interpret these
hidden states
원문 의미: is it's a representation of the 시퀀스
process so far.
is it's a representation of the sequence process
so far.
원문 의미: 그래서 the good thing with RNN is now
the word order matters.
So the good thing with RNNs is now the word
order matters.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're also able to encode the
sentence
And you're also able to encode the sentence
원문 의미: in a more natural way.
in a more natural way.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's see roughly how it works.
So let's see roughly how it works.
원문 의미: 그래서 we have the same favorite 예시,
So we have the same favorite example,
원문 의미: 그래서 cute teddy bear is reading.
so cute teddy bear is reading.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would have the 토큰 A. You
want one-hot encoding
So you would have the token A. You want one-hot
encoding
벡터.
vector.
원문 의미: You pass it through your network.
You pass it through your network.
원문 의미: You compute the hidden state.
You compute the hidden state.
원문 의미: You try to predict cute.
You try to predict cute.
원문 의미: 하지만 then you keep track of the
hidden state.
But then you keep track of the hidden state.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you 입력 that into another
module.
And then you input that into another module.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you also consider the next
words.
And then you also consider the next words.
원문 의미: 그래서 you consider not only the word
itself, but also the hidden
So you consider not only the word itself, but
also the hidden
원문 의미: state of this sentence so far.
state of this sentence so far.
원문 의미: 그리고 you try to predict the next
word again, and again and again.
And you try to predict the next word again, and
again and again.
그래서 this is RNN.
So this is RNN.
원문 의미: 그래서 RNN were used for a bunch of
tasks,
So RNNs were used for a bunch of tasks,
원문 의미: 그리고 just like mapping that back to
the categories
and just like mapping that back to the
categories
that 우리가 보았습니다 before.
that we saw before.
원문 의미: For 분류 purposes, you can basically
For classification purposes, you can basically
원문 의미: use the hidden state of the last
word in your sentence.
use the hidden state of the last word in your
sentence.
For instance, if 여러분은 predict
For instance, if you want to predict
원문 의미: like the sentiment of a review, you
like the sentiment of a review, you
원문 의미: would take basically the last 벡터
here
would take basically the last vector here
원문 의미: 그리고 try to project it into the
space
and try to project it into the space
원문 의미: of the predictions or the labels
that 여러분은 predict on.
of the predictions or the labels that you want
to predict on.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, if you want
positive or negative,
So for instance, if you want positive or
negative,
원문 의미: you basically project that 벡터 onto
that space.
you basically project that vector onto that
space.
원문 의미: You can do that here.
You can do that here.
원문 의미: For multi-분류, so you would
basically
For multi-classification, so you would basically
원문 의미: have the representation of the 토큰
of interest,
have the representation of the token of
interest,
원문 의미: 그리고 you would project that.
and you would project that.
원문 의미: Or for 생성, you would basically
Or for generation, you would basically
원문 의미: process the whole source text, and
then
process the whole source text, and then
have a 문맥 벡터, a.k.a.
have a context vector, a.k.a.
원문 의미: activation 벡터, a.k.a.
activation vector, a.k.a.
원문 의미: hidden state at the end of your
processing,
hidden state at the end of your processing,
원문 의미: which will then be used to decode
the 출력 prediction.
which will then be used to decode the output
prediction.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is how you would use an
RNN 각각에 대해 of these tasks.
So this is how you would use an RNN for each of
these tasks.
원문 의미: 그래서 the reason why you have not
really heard of RNN these days
So the reason why you have not really heard of
RNNs these days
원문 의미: is because they had some pros, but
많은 cons.
is because they had some pros, but a lot of
cons.
원문 의미: 그래서 그중 하나의 cons is that the meaning
of the sentence
So one of the cons is that the meaning of the
sentence
원문 의미: is basically solely encapsulated
into this hidden state.
is basically solely encapsulated into this
hidden state.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have this problem of
long-range dependencies,
So you have this problem of long-range
dependencies,
원문 의미: which basically impacts your
ability to quote, unquote,
which basically impacts your ability to quote,
unquote,
원문 의미: "remember" what the 모델 saw in the
past,
"remember" what the model saw in the past,
원문 의미: which is why you have another 수업 of
모델 that try
which is why you have another class of models
that try
원문 의미: to build on RNN.
to build on RNNs.
원문 의미: 그래서 this one is called LSTM, Long
Short-Term Memory.
So this one is called LSTMs, Long Short-Term
Memory.
원문 의미: 그리고 the goal of that extension is
to have the way to somehow
And the goal of that extension is to have the
way to somehow
원문 의미: keep track of the things that are
quote, unquote, "important"
keep track of the things that are quote,
unquote, "important"
원문 의미: to remember, on top of the hidden
state that we talked
to remember, on top of the hidden state that we
talked
about.
원문 의미: 그래서 here you have a of t, which is
your activation,
So here you have a of t, which is your
activation,
원문 의미: basically the 시퀀스 so far encoded in
there.
basically the sequence so far encoded in there.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have another quantity
And then you have another quantity
원문 의미: that you track that is called the
cell state.
that you track that is called the cell state.
원문 의미: It's denoted c here.
It's denoted c here.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 아키텍처 aims at improving
that piece,
So this architecture aims at improving that
piece,
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess it was not perfect
either.
but I guess it was not perfect either.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, so that was the main
issue
But yeah, so that was the main issue
원문 의미: of RNN-based methods, which is that
they
of RNN-based methods, which is that they
원문 의미: have this issue of forgetting what
was in the past.
have this issue of forgetting what was in the
past.
원문 의미: 그래서 you will see in the literature
So you will see in the literature
원문 의미: that this phenomenon is called
vanishing 그래디언트.
that this phenomenon is called vanishing
gradient.
원문 의미: 그리고 the reason why it's called that
way— so I know we're
And the reason why it's called that way-- so I
know we're
원문 의미: running 중에서 time, but I'm ~할 예정입니다
just explain that part.
running out of time, but I'm going to just
explain that part.
원문 의미: 그래서 in order for you to predict,
let's say, the last words,
So in order for you to predict, let's say, the
last words,
원문 의미: you're basically dependent on every
hidden state
you're basically dependent on every hidden state
원문 의미: that came before that.
that came before that.
그래서 far so good?
So far so good?
그리고 so whenever 여러분은 update the 가중치 of
your 모델
And so whenever you want to update the weights
of your model
원문 의미: to match the prediction here with
the actual prediction, when
to match the prediction here with the actual
prediction, when
원문 의미: you do the back propagation, you
somehow
you do the back propagation, you somehow
원문 의미: need to take into account that the
값 here is basically
need to take into account that the value here is
basically
원문 의미: not only a matter of this
computation,
not only a matter of this computation,
원문 의미: 하지만 also this computation or this
computation
but also this computation or this computation
원문 의미: that basically happened in a
sequential manner.
that basically happened in a sequential manner.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have this phenomenon of
trying to, I guess,
So you have this phenomenon of trying to, I
guess,
원문 의미: back-propagate through time.
back-propagate through time.
원문 의미: 하지만 the problem is, in practice
when
But the problem is, in practice when
원문 의미: you write that down— so it's a very
ugly formula.
you write that down-- so it's a very ugly
formula.
원문 의미: 하지만 when you write that down, it
ends up
But when you write that down, it ends up
원문 의미: being a product of a bunch of
quantities
being a product of a bunch of quantities
원문 의미: that can— so if it's greater than
1, then it's exploding.
that can-- so if it's greater than 1, then it's
exploding.
원문 의미: If it's less than 1, it's
vanishing.
If it's less than 1, it's vanishing.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 if you multiply 많은 things that
are less than 1,
Because if you multiply a lot of things that are
less than 1,
원문 의미: it just goes to 0.
it just goes to 0.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess if you have something
that you're
So I guess if you have something that you're
원문 의미: trying to update that goes to 0,
basically
trying to update that goes to 0, basically
원문 의미: you have trouble just doing your
updates.
you have trouble just doing your updates.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's a high-level intuition.
So that's a high-level intuition.
원문 의미: This is not the focus of this 수업,
This is not the focus of this class,
원문 의미: which is why I'm not going into the
detail
which is why I'm not going into the detail
원문 의미: of this ugly formulas.
of this ugly formulas.
원문 의미: 하지만 I hope you get the idea that
for remembering things
But I hope you get the idea that for remembering
things
원문 의미: from the past, it's not doing a
great job,
from the past, it's not doing a great job,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 of this sequential, I guess,
characteristic.
because of this sequential, I guess,
이해되나요?
Does that make sense?
원문 의미: OK, I hope the next thing will make
a bit more sense.
OK, I hope the next thing will make a bit more
sense.
원문 의미: 하지만 before that, I'll just recap
what 우리가 보았습니다.
But before that, I'll just recap what we saw.
원문 의미: 그래서 our goal is to represent text.
So our goal is to represent text.
원문 의미: 그래서 we first started with
representing
So we first started with representing
원문 의미: words or 토큰, which was what we
tried to do with Word2vec.
words or tokens, which was what we tried to do
with Word2vec.
원문 의미: 그리고 우리가 보았습니다 that it was a good
way to leverage proxy tasks
And we saw that it was a good way to leverage
proxy tasks
원문 의미: to learn this representation.
to learn this representation.
원문 의미: 하지만 we had a bunch of limitations.
But we had a bunch of limitations.
원문 의미: 그리고 그중 하나의m that you mentioned
And one of them that you mentioned
원문 의미: was that this was not aware of the
문맥.
was that this was not aware of the context.
원문 의미: 그리고 also the word order didn't
count.
And also the word order didn't count.
원문 의미: 그리고 so you have this other 수업 of
methods
And so you have this other class of methods
원문 의미: that is able to take into
consideration the words,
that is able to take into consideration the
words,
원문 의미: 하지만 then they have some trouble
keeping track of things
but then they have some trouble keeping track of
things
원문 의미: when the 시퀀스 gets very long.
when the sequence gets very long.
원문 의미: 그리고 you have this problem of
vanishing 그래디언트s
And you have this problem of vanishing gradients
원문 의미: or long-range dependencies.
or long-range dependencies.
원문 의미: 그래서 whenever you see this term,
it's
So whenever you see this term, it's
원문 의미: basically referring to that.
basically referring to that.
원문 의미: 그리고 also another thing that I have
not mentioned,
And also another thing that I have not
mentioned,
원문 의미: 하지만 the computations are very slow.
but the computations are very slow.
그래서 when 여러분은 학습하다 these 모델, at 학습 time,
So when you want to train these models, at
training time,
원문 의미: in order to predict this word, you
basically
in order to predict this word, you basically
원문 의미: need to compute all these hidden
states before.
need to compute all these hidden states before.
원문 의미: 그래서 when your 시퀀스 gets very long,
So when your sequence gets very long,
원문 의미: it just takes a very long time.
it just takes a very long time.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 모든se reasons, for I guess
what reason.
So for all of these reasons, for I guess what
reason.
원문 의미: 그래서 for the fact that the 모델 has
trouble remembering things
So for the fact that the model has trouble
remembering things
원문 의미: from the past, people have tried
having more direct connections
from the past, people have tried having more
direct connections
원문 의미: between something and the thing
from the past,
between something and the thing from the past,
원문 의미: 그리고 this is the idea behind 어텐션.
and this is the idea behind attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 what 어텐션 does is it tries
So what attention does is it tries
원문 의미: to have a direct link between what
we're trying to predict
to have a direct link between what we're trying
to predict
원문 의미: 그리고 something from the past.
and something from the past.
원문 의미: 그래서 in this 예시, let's suppose
So in this example, let's suppose
원문 의미: I'm trying to translate an English
sentence
I'm trying to translate an English sentence
원문 의미: into a French one.
into a French one.
원문 의미: 그래서 here I guess the 입력 sentence is
given.
So here I guess the input sentence is given.
원문 의미: I'm computing the hidden state.
I'm computing the hidden state.
원문 의미: I'm processing words one at a time.
I'm processing words one at a time.
원문 의미: This is my traditional RNN.
This is my traditional RNN.
원문 의미: 그래서 "a cute teddy bear is reading."
So "a cute teddy bear is reading."
원문 의미: 그래서 here I have a hidden state that
I'm then decoding.
So here I have a hidden state that I'm then
decoding.
원문 의미: 그리고 you can imagine that when
wanting
And you can imagine that when wanting
원문 의미: to generate the next word of my
translation,
to generate the next word of my translation,
원문 의미: it would be great if I knew what
word I'm trying to predict.
it would be great if I knew what word I'm trying
to predict.
원문 의미: Or in other words, it would be
great
Or in other words, it would be great
원문 의미: if I could take a peek at a certain
area of the 입력 텍스트.
if I could take a peek at a certain area of the
input text.
원문 의미: 그래서 the idea behind 어텐션 is to have
So the idea behind attention is to have
원문 의미: a direct link between what you're
trying to predict
a direct link between what you're trying to
predict
원문 의미: 그리고 things before.
and things before.
원문 의미: This is the idea behind 어텐션.
This is the idea behind attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 so it was introduced in 2014.
And so it was introduced in 2014.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah, again, this is trying to
solve
And yeah, again, this is trying to solve
원문 의미: for these long-range dependency
issues.
for these long-range dependency issues.
그리고 so yeah, this 예시 우리는 do that.
And so yeah, this example we want to do that.
원문 의미: 그리고 this concept is ~할 예정입니다
actually be 키 for this 수업.
And this concept is going to actually be key for
this class.
왜냐하면 we're ~할 예정입니다 see that the 어텐션 메커니즘
is
Because we're going to see that the attention
mechanism is
원문 의미: the thing that is ~할 예정입니다 make
everything—
the thing that is going to make everything--
원문 의미: I mean, most of the things work.
I mean, most of the things work.
원문 의미: 그리고 this is actually the main
principle
And this is actually the main principle
원문 의미: that the 트랜스포머 paper relies on.
that the transformer paper relies on.
그래서 the 트랜스포머, which is the core 아키텍처
So the transformer, which is the core
architecture
that 우리가 볼 것입니다 이 수업에서, has been
introduced
that we will see in this class, has been
원문 의미: or was introduced in 2017 in this
paper named
or was introduced in 2017 in this paper named
원문 의미: 어텐션 is All You Need.
Attention is All You Need.
원문 의미: 그래서 even from the title, 여러분이 볼 수
있습니다 that the authors wanted
So even from the title, you can see that the
authors wanted
원문 의미: to just rely on that part.
to just rely on that part.
원문 의미: 그래서 what the authors tried to do
was
So what the authors tried to do was
원문 의미: to move away from this sequential
way of processing
to move away from this sequential way of
processing
원문 의미: the text, and instead let the 모델
just
the text, and instead let the model just
원문 의미: have direct connections with all
parts of the text at once.
have direct connections with all parts of the
text at once.
그래서 that is called 셀프 어텐션.
So that is called self-attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 they tried that on translation
tasks.
So they tried that on translation tasks.
원문 의미: 그리고 they just realized that it was
giving great results.
And they just realized that it was giving great
results.
원문 의미: 그래서 back to the 예시 that we're still
using,
So back to the example that we're still using,
원문 의미: a cute teddy bear is reading Here
what we would say
a cute teddy bear is reading Here what we would
say
원문 의미: is that in order to compute the
representation
is that in order to compute the representation
원문 의미: of the 토큰 teddy bear, we're going
of the token teddy bear, we're going
원문 의미: to look at all the other 토큰 in the
시퀀스 at once,
to look at all the other tokens in the sequence
at once,
원문 의미: 그리고 directly with direct links.
and directly with direct links.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess back to your question—
here,
So I guess back to your question-- here,
원문 의미: we would have a representation of
teddy bear
we would have a representation of teddy bear
원문 의미: that would be unique to the 문맥 that
it is part of.
that would be unique to the context that it is
part of.
원문 의미: 그래서 back to your question about
riverbank and robbing a bank,
So back to your question about riverbank and
robbing a bank,
원문 의미: like here the bank would have
different representations.
like here the bank would have different
representations.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is the idea.
So this is the idea.
원문 의미: I guess, does the idea roughly 말이
됩니다?
I guess, does the idea roughly make sense?
그리고 again, this is called the 셀프 어텐션 메커니즘.
And again, this is called the self-attention
mechanism.
원문 의미: Afshine, how am I doing on time?
Afshine, how am I doing on time?
8.
I have 8?
OK, cool.
원문 의미: OK, so this is the idea.
OK, so this is the idea.
그래서 now I'm ~할 예정입니다 just introduce
So now I'm going to just introduce
원문 의미: another set of ideas which is more
terminology
another set of ideas which is more terminology
하지만 is ~할 예정입니다 be very important.
but is going to be very important.
원문 의미: 그래서 when 여러분은 express something in
terms of something
So when you want to express something in terms
of something
원문 의미: else, we use the words "쿼리," "키,"
and "값," Q, K and V.
else, we use the words "query," "key," and
"value," Q, K and V.
원문 의미: 그래서 in this 예시, our goal is to
figure out
So in this example, our goal is to figure out
원문 의미: what other 토큰 is the 쿼리 teddy bear
more similar to.
what other tokens is the query teddy bear more
similar to.
원문 의미: 그래서 here the question is, OK, you
have a 쿼리
So here the question is, OK, you have a query
그리고 여러분은 see what other 토큰 are most
similar.
and you want to see what other tokens are most
그리고 so what you're ~할 예정입니다 do is
And so what you're going to do is
원문 의미: to look at all the other 토큰 which
are basically
to look at all the other tokens which are
basically
원문 의미: composed of 키 and 값.
composed of keys and values.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 compare the 쿼리 to the 키
So we're going to compare the query to the key
원문 의미: to quantify how similar your 쿼리 is
to a given 키,
to quantify how similar your query is to a given
key,
원문 의미: 그리고 take the corresponding 값.
and take the corresponding value.
원문 의미: 그래서 we'll see that in this 예시,
So we'll see that in this example,
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose 여러분은 express
teddy bear in terms
so let's suppose you want to express teddy bear
in terms
원문 의미: of everything else.
of everything else.
원문 의미: What you're ~할 예정입니다 do is you're
What you're going to do is you're
~할 예정입니다 take the 쿼리 teddy bear,
going to take the query teddy bear,
원문 의미: 그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 compare that 쿼리
with all the other 키
and you're going to compare that query with all
the other keys
원문 의미: to see which element is most
similar,
to see which element is most similar,
원문 의미: 그리고 then 가중치 the more similar ones
and then weight the more similar ones
원문 의미: 그리고 take their associated 값.
and take their associated value.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's a very 큰 틀 idea of how
these things are.
So that's a very high level idea of how these
things are.
원문 의미: 물론 we're ~할 예정입니다 see exactly how
they work.
Of course, we're going to see exactly how they
work.
원문 의미: 하지만 that's the general idea.
But that's the general idea.
OK, cool.
원문 의미: 그리고 speaking of 쿼리 and 키 and 값,
And speaking of query and key and value,
원문 의미: we will also see that one benefit
of expressing things
we will also see that one benefit of expressing
things
원문 의미: this way is that we can express
doing
this way is that we can express doing
원문 의미: this 셀프 어텐션 computation across the
whole 시퀀스
this self-attention computation across the whole
sequence
in a 행렬 format.
in a matrix format.
그리고 GPUs love 행렬들.
And GPUs love matrices.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's really made for the
hardware that we have.
So it's really made for the hardware that we
have.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess what I mentioned here
And I guess what I mentioned here
원문 의미: can be expressed in a form of 소프트맥스
can be expressed in a form of softmax
원문 의미: of the 쿼리 and the 키, which is
basically a way
of the query and the key, which is basically a
way
원문 의미: to get some kinds of 가중치 of which 값
to get some kinds of weights of which values
원문 의미: will be more important.
will be more important.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, if a 값 is more
important,
So for instance, if a value is more important,
원문 의미: you have bigger 가중치.
you have bigger weight.
원문 의미: 그리고 another one will be less
important,
And another one will be less important,
원문 의미: you'll have a smaller 가중치.
you'll have a smaller weight.
원문 의미: 그리고 you basically multiply that by
the 값.
And you basically multiply that by the value.
원문 의미: 그래서 don't worry, we'll have a
detailed 예시 after.
So don't worry, we'll have a detailed example
after.
원문 의미: 그래서 if it still feels very
high-level fuzzy, don't worry.
So if it still feels very high-level fuzzy,
don't worry.
원문 의미: We'll have a detailed walkthrough.
We'll have a detailed walkthrough.
원문 의미: 그리고 yes, so this is how it works.
And yes, so this is how it works.
OK, cool.
원문 의미: Any questions on what 셀프 어텐션 is?
Any questions on what self-attention is?
네.
Yeah.
원문 의미: Great, great question.
Great, great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is, what is 값,
what is 키?
So the question is, what is value, what is key?
원문 의미: I guess, how to get those?
I guess, how to get those?
원문 의미: What do they mean?
What do they mean?
원문 의미: 그래서 first of all, I just want to
say that these quantities,
So first of all, I just want to say that these
quantities,
원문 의미: they are learned.
they are learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 you are not fixing them.
So you are not fixing them.
원문 의미: 하지만 from an interpretation
standpoint,
But from an interpretation standpoint,
원문 의미: you can interpret that the 키 is
there
you can interpret that the key is there
원문 의미: for you to figure out which one is
most similar to the 쿼리.
for you to figure out which one is most similar
to the query.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 값 is the actual 값
And the value is the actual value
원문 의미: that is associated with that
element.
that is associated with that element.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, you will have something
like you
So here, you will have something like you
원문 의미: want to express this in terms of
all the 값.
want to express this in terms of all the values.
그래서 the 가중치 in your 가중치ed average
So the weights in your weighted average
원문 의미: will be basically the dot product
between—
will be basically the dot product between--
원문 의미: basically— between the 쿼리 and the
키.
basically-- between the query and the key.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 값 will be the actual 벡터
that you will use.
And the value will be the actual vector that you
will use.
원문 의미: 하지만 again, these things are
learned.
But again, these things are learned.
원문 의미: 그리고 something I have not mentioned,
And something I have not mentioned,
원문 의미: 하지만 you mentioned it correctly, so
we're
but you mentioned it correctly, so we're
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 actually do projections to
obtain these quantities.
going to actually do projections to obtain these
quantities.
원문 의미: 그리고 these projections are actually
learned by the 모델.
And these projections are actually learned by
the model.
That's good?
OK, cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 with that, we have 15 minutes,
right,
So with that, we have 15 minutes, right,
원문 의미: to talk about the 아키텍처.
to talk about the architecture.
OK, so 아주 큰 틀에서, in order
OK, so at a very high level, in order
to make the 셀프 어텐션 메커니즘 happen,
to make the self-attention mechanism happen,
원문 의미: the authors propose an 아키텍처
the authors propose an architecture
원문 의미: that is composed of two parts, an
인코더, which
that is composed of two parts, an encoder, which
원문 의미: is on the left side, and a 디코더,
is on the left side, and a decoder,
원문 의미: which is on the right side.
which is on the right side.
원문 의미: 그래서 the application that they have
is translation.
So the application that they have is
translation.
원문 의미: 그래서 what will go through the 인코더
So what will go through the encoder
원문 의미: is the 입력 텍스트 in your source
language.
is the input text in your source language.
그리고 what is ~할 예정입니다 go through the 디코더
And what is going to go through the decoder
원문 의미: is the target language that you're
predicting.
is the target language that you're predicting.
원문 의미: 그래서 the high-level idea is you're
going
So the high-level idea is you're going
원문 의미: to compute meaningful 임베딩 from your
입력 텍스트
to compute meaningful embeddings from your input
text
원문 의미: by passing them through the 인코더.
by passing them through the encoder.
그리고 you want that 셀프 어텐션 메커니즘 to apply,
And you want that self-attention mechanism to
apply,
원문 의미: meaning 여러분은 compute
representations of each 토큰
meaning you want to compute representations of
each token
원문 의미: as a function of others.
as a function of others.
원문 의미: 그리고 you do that by using a layer
called the 어텐션 layer.
And you do that by using a layer called the
attention layer.
그래서 멀티헤드 어텐션 layer, but 멀티헤드
So multi-head attention layer, but multi-head
원문 의미: is just doing this computation in
different ways
is just doing this computation in different ways
원문 의미: to just allow the 모델 to learn
different representations
to just allow the model to learn different
representations
원문 의미: or different projections.
or different projections.
하지만 the idea here is you are ~할 예정입니다 입력
your 입력 텍스트,
But the idea here is you are going to input your
input text,
그리고 all the 토큰 in your 입력 텍스트
and all the tokens in your input text
원문 의미: are ~할 예정입니다 attend to one another.
are going to attend to one another.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, a cute teddy bear
is reading,
So for instance, a cute teddy bear is reading,
원문 의미: you are ~할 예정입니다 compute the
representation
you are going to compute the representation
원문 의미: of all the 토큰 in this text
basically
of all the tokens in this text basically
원문 의미: as a function of others.
as a function of others.
그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 do that with the 인코더,
so here
And you're going to do that with the encoder, so
here
with the 멀티헤드 어텐션.
with the multi-head attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have a feedforward
layer,
And then you have a feedforward layer,
원문 의미: which is just to let the 모델 learn
which is just to let the model learn
원문 의미: another 일종의 projection.
another kind of projection.
원문 의미: 그리고 what you're ~할 예정입니다 obtain at
the end
And what you're going to obtain at the end
원문 의미: of your encoding process is rich
representations
of your encoding process is rich representations
원문 의미: of the 토큰 from the 입력 sentence.
of the tokens from the input sentence.
그래서 far, so good?
So far, so good?
원문 의미: 하지만 now your goal is to actually
translate the 입력 sentence.
But now your goal is to actually translate the
input sentence.
원문 의미: 그래서 what you're ~할 예정입니다 do is to
start your translation
So what you're going to do is to start your
translation
원문 의미: with, let's suppose, the beginning
of sentence 토큰,
with, let's suppose, the beginning of sentence
token,
그래서 your first 토큰.
so your first token.
원문 의미: 그리고 what you're ~할 예정입니다 do is use
all the representations
And what you're going to do is use all the
representations
원문 의미: from your 입력 sentence in order
from your input sentence in order
원문 의미: to figure out what to predict next.
to figure out what to predict next.
원문 의미: 그래서 this what I just said is the
cross-어텐션 layer,
So this what I just said is the cross-attention
layer,
원문 의미: which is the one that is the
second, so this one,
which is the one that is the second, so this
one,
원문 의미: which basically—
which basically--
원문 의미: I'm not sure if you see the arrows,
I'm not sure if you see the arrows,
원문 의미: 하지만 there are two arrows coming
from the 인코더, one
but there are two arrows coming from the
encoder, one
원문 의미: arrow coming from the 디코더.
arrow coming from the decoder.
원문 의미: Can anyone tell me what the arrow
from the 디코더
Can anyone tell me what the arrow from the
decoder
represents?
Is 디코더 a 쿼리 키 or 값?
Is decoder a query key or value?
원문 의미: I guess there is 1 over 3, 33%
chance.
I guess there is 1 over 3, 33% chance.
원문 의미: Who wants to try?
Who wants to try?
Is it 키?
Is it key?
좋습니다.
OK.
쿼리?
Query?
좋습니다.
OK.
원문 의미: 그래서 the way to think about it is
you're
So the way to think about it is you're
원문 의미: trying to ask yourself, what are
the words from the 입력 that
trying to ask yourself, what are the words from
the input that
matter.
Right?
원문 의미: 그래서 basically, you want know, given
So basically, you want know, given
원문 의미: your 쿼리, what are the elements from
the 입력s that
your query, what are the elements from the
inputs that
matter?
원문 의미: 그래서 here, this arrow is indeed the
쿼리,
So here, this arrow is indeed the query,
왜냐하면 this is the thing that 여러분은 figure
out.
because this is the thing that you want to
figure out.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 키 and 값 are actually
And the keys and values are actually
원문 의미: coming from the 인코더, which are
basically
coming from the encoder, which are basically
원문 의미: coming from the 입력 시퀀스.
coming from the input sequence.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have another 어텐션
layer,
And then you have another attention layer,
원문 의미: which is this one.
which is this one.
원문 의미: 그리고 that one is trying to figure
out
And that one is trying to figure out
원문 의미: what other 토큰 of the 출력 sentence
that you're decoding
what other tokens of the output sentence that
you're decoding
원문 의미: is ~할 예정입니다 be useful to predict
the next 토큰.
is going to be useful to predict the next token.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you start
decoding
So let's suppose you start decoding
원문 의미: 그리고 you say, un ours en peluche,
which is in French.
and you say, un ours en peluche, which is in
French.
원문 의미: To predict the next word, 여러분은
basically figure out
To predict the next word, you want to basically
figure out
원문 의미: what are the 토큰 translated so far
that
what are the tokens translated so far that
원문 의미: are ~할 예정입니다 be useful to predict
the next word.
are going to be useful to predict the next word.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is what this 어텐션 layer is
about.
So this is what this attention layer is about.
원문 의미: 그리고 it's called masked, because it
only
And it's called masked, because it only
원문 의미: looks at the 토큰 that translated so
far.
looks at the tokens that translated so far.
원문 의미: It does not look at 토큰 that were
not
It does not look at tokens that were not
원문 의미: translated, because of 강좌 they were
not translated.
translated, because of course they were not
translated.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's no way, like on the
right side of the 토큰
So there's no way, like on the right side of the
token
원문 의미: that you're trying to predict.
that you're trying to predict.
좋습니다.
Cool.
그래서 아주 큰 틀에서, you have this 어텐션 layer,
So at a very high level, you have this attention
layer,
원문 의미: which is present in the 인코더, which
is present in the 디코더,
which is present in the encoder, which is
present in the decoder,
원문 의미: 하지만 it has several, I guess, use
cases.
but it has several, I guess, use cases.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 어텐션 layer here aims at
computing 임베딩
So the attention layer here aims at computing
embeddings
원문 의미: from the 입력 sentence as a function
of themselves.
from the input sentence as a function of
themselves.
원문 의미: 그리고 then the ones from the 디코더,
And then the ones from the decoder,
원문 의미: 그래서 the first one, the masked 셀프
어텐션 layer,
so the first one, the masked self-attention
layer,
원문 의미: aims at expressing something as a
function of everything that
aims at expressing something as a function of
everything that
원문 의미: has been decoded so far.
has been decoded so far.
원문 의미: 그리고 the second one, the cross-어텐션
layer,
And the second one, the cross-attention layer,
원문 의미: tries to express things as a
function of what
tries to express things as a function of what
원문 의미: has been seen in the 입력.
has been seen in the input.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, given that you are having
So here, given that you are having
원문 의미: direct links to different 토큰,
direct links to different tokens,
원문 의미: you don't have this sense of order.
you don't have this sense of order.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 in the RNN, you are basically
Because in the RNN, you are basically
원문 의미: expressing things one at a time.
expressing things one at a time.
원문 의미: 그래서 you had some sense of the word
order,
So you had some sense of the word order,
원문 의미: 하지만 here you don't have it, because
it's
but here you don't have it, because it's
원문 의미: like a direct link, which is why
you have position
like a direct link, which is why you have
position
원문 의미: encodings, which are there to
inform
encodings, which are there to inform
원문 의미: on the position of the word in the
시퀀스.
on the position of the word in the sequence.
원문 의미: 그래서 we're not ~할 예정입니다 dig into
that today,
So we're not going to dig into that today,
원문 의미: 하지만 I just want to call that out.
but I just want to call that out.
그래서 아주 큰 틀에서, and we're
So at a very high level, and we're
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 see this in the detailed
예시, what
going to see this in the detailed example, what
원문 의미: we do is in order to translate a
sentence from source language
we do is in order to translate a sentence from
source language
원문 의미: to target language, we're first
going
to target language, we're first going
원문 의미: to 토큰ize the text, so dividing into
arbitrary units.
to tokenize the text, so dividing into arbitrary
units.
이제 learn an embedding for these tokens.을/를
보겠습니다.
We're going to learn an embedding for these
tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is what the 입력 임베딩 is
about.
So this is what the input embedding is about.
원문 의미: 그러면 we're ~할 예정입니다 add some
encoding with respect
Then we're going to add some encoding with
respect
원문 의미: to the position.
to the position.
원문 의미: We're not ~할 예정입니다 talk about it
today, but just good to note.
We're not going to talk about it today, but just
good to note.
원문 의미: 그리고 then we go through the 인코더.
And then we go through the encoder.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 인코더 tries to figure out
So the encoder tries to figure out
원문 의미: how to express things as a function
of other things
how to express things as a function of other
things
from the 입력s.
from the inputs.
그래서 it does that in the 멀티헤드 어텐션 layer.
So it does that in the multi-head attention
layer.
원문 의미: 그리고 then it goes through a
feedforward 신경망,
And then it goes through a feedforward neural
network,
원문 의미: which is just a way to just project
the 벡터 to just
which is just a way to just project the vectors
to just
원문 의미: have some more degrees of freedom
to learn things.
have some more degrees of freedom to learn
things.
원문 의미: 그리고 then once you have these
representations from the 입력,
And then once you have these representations
from the input,
원문 의미: you're then ~할 예정입니다 start your
translation.
you're then going to start your translation.
원문 의미: 그래서 you start with the BOS 토큰.
So you start with the BOS token.
원문 의미: 그리고 what you're trying to do is
figure
And what you're trying to do is figure
원문 의미: out what the next word is.
out what the next word is.
그래서 you're ~할 예정입니다 see, OK, what are
So you're going to see, OK, what are
원문 의미: the words that were translated so
far that
the words that were translated so far that
원문 의미: are useful for translation.
are useful for translation.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is what the masked 멀티헤드
어텐션 layer does.
So this is what the masked multi-head attention
layer does.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have another 어텐션
layer,
And then you have another attention layer,
원문 의미: which is about expressing things as
a function of what
which is about expressing things as a function
of what
원문 의미: was in the 입력, which is the
cross-어텐션 layer
was in the input, which is the cross-attention
layer
over there.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have a feedforward 신경망
to, again,
And then you have a feedforward neural network
원문 의미: give some more degrees of freedom.
give some more degrees of freedom.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the end of the day, you have
a 벡터 that you then
And at the end of the day, you have a vector
that you then
go through 소프트맥스.
go through softmax.
원문 의미: 그리고 it just is a way for you to
guess what is the next word.
And it just is a way for you to guess what is
the next word.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have a 벡터 of vocabulary
size.
So you have a vector of vocabulary size.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 use these 값 to
determine
And you're going to use these values to
원문 의미: what is your next word.
what is your next word.
Easy, right?
원문 의미: Any questions on this?
Any questions on this?
네.
Yeah.
원문 의미: All right, that's a great question.
All right, that's a great question.
원문 의미: The question is, what does head
mean?
The question is, what does head mean?
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess I went too fast.
So I guess I went too fast.
원문 의미: I ignored that part.
I ignored that part.
원문 의미: 하지만 when you do the 셀프 어텐션
computation,
But when you do the self-attention computation,
원문 의미: you basically make 쿼리들 interact
with 키,
you basically make queries interact with keys,
원문 의미: 그리고 then take the corresponding 값.
and then take the corresponding value.
원문 의미: 하지만 nothing prevents you from doing
that several times.
But nothing prevents you from doing that several
times.
원문 의미: 그래서 the term "head" is given to the
projection 행렬들 that you
So the term "head" is given to the projection
matrices that you
원문 의미: use to obtain the 쿼리, 키, and 값.
use to obtain the query, key, and value.
원문 의미: 그리고 when you have several heads,
what you're doing
And when you have several heads, what you're
doing
원문 의미: is you're allowing your 모델 to learn
different projections.
is you're allowing your model to learn different
projections.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's basically an additional
degree
So it's basically an additional degree
원문 의미: of freedom for your 모델 to learn
different associations
of freedom for your model to learn different
associations
원문 의미: between your 벡터.
between your vectors.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's a great question.
So it's a great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically it will be noted
lowercase h, number of heads.
So typically it will be noted lowercase h,
number of heads.
원문 의미: 그리고 this is what this corresponds
to.
And this is what this corresponds to.
원문 의미: Does that answer your question?
Does that answer your question?
원문 의미: Cool, very cool.
Cool, very cool.
원문 의미: OK, we have a lot to discuss, but
here I
OK, we have a lot to discuss, but here I
원문 의미: had the slide actually for this.
had the slide actually for this.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is the 멀티헤드s that you were
mentioning.
So this is the multi-heads that you were
원문 의미: 그래서 we're basically running the 셀프
어텐션 computation
So we're basically running the self-attention
computation
원문 의미: several times in parallel, again,
several times in parallel, again,
원문 의미: with different projection 행렬들 that
the 모델 learns.
with different projection matrices that the
model learns.
원문 의미: 그래서 in case you have a computer
vision background,
So in case you have a computer vision
background,
원문 의미: it is similar to having multiple
filters in your convolution.
it is similar to having multiple filters in your
convolution.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's the same idea, but it's
different here.
So it's the same idea, but it's different here.
원문 의미: Yeah, great question.
Yeah, great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is, are the
projections different?
So the question is, are the projections
different?
원문 의미: 그래서 we're typically not cons학습
things.
So we're typically not constraining things.
원문 의미: We're just letting the 모델 learn.
We're just letting the model learn.
원문 의미: 하지만 in practice, it just tends to
learn different ways
But in practice, it just tends to learn
different ways
원문 의미: of saying the same thing.
of saying the same thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, typically there is no
cons학습하다t.
So yeah, typically there is no constraint.
원문 의미: 물론 you have papers that dig into
how about
Of course, you have papers that dig into how
about
원문 의미: if you change this.
if you change this.
원문 의미: 하지만 typically you don't have any
cons학습하다t.
But typically you don't have any constraint.
Cool, great.
원문 의미: OK, I will just mention one trick,
OK, I will just mention one trick,
원문 의미: another trick that the 트랜스포머
authors use.
another trick that the transformer authors use.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's called label smoothing.
So it's called label smoothing.
원문 의미: Who has heard of label smoothing?
Who has heard of label smoothing?
원문 의미: 그래서 one new thing here is in NLP
when
So one new thing here is in NLP when
여러분은 predict what comes next,
you want to predict what comes next,
원문 의미: there's typically more than one
way.
there's typically more than one way.
원문 의미: When you say, what a great day,
what
When you say, what a great day, what
원문 의미: a great 강의, what a great book, what
a great—
a great lecture, what a great book, what a
great--
원문 의미: there's always multiple choices.
there's always multiple choices.
원문 의미: There's more than one way of
filling that gap.
There's more than one way of filling that gap.
원문 의미: 그래서 label smoothing is a technique
So label smoothing is a technique
원문 의미: that tries to intuitively address
that.
that tries to intuitively address that.
원문 의미: 그리고 what it does is, instead of
saying predict this word 100%
And what it does is, instead of saying predict
this word 100%
원문 의미: is this one, there is no other
words, what it does is it says,
is this one, there is no other words, what it
does is it says,
원문 의미: predict this word, but there's a
chance it's not this word.
predict this word, but there's a chance it's not
this word.
원문 의미: 그리고 in practice, what it does is it
takes the one-hot encoding.
And in practice, what it does is it takes the
one-hot encoding.
원문 의미: 그리고 instead of saying it's a 1, 0,
0, 0,
And instead of saying it's a 1, 0, 0, 0,
원문 의미: that 여러분은 predict, it says it's
actually
that you need to predict, it says it's actually
원문 의미: 1 minus epsilon, and then epsilon
over v minus 1, I guess,
1 minus epsilon, and then epsilon over v minus
1, I guess,
원문 의미: is you're trying to predict.
is you're trying to predict.
원문 의미: 그래서 in practice, it's a method that
So in practice, it's a method that
원문 의미: tends to make your 모델 be more
unsure.
tends to make your model be more unsure.
원문 의미: Again, to be less sure about this
prediction
Again, to be less sure about this prediction
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you always tell it, OK, try to
predict this,
because you always tell it, OK, try to predict
this,
원문 의미: 하지만 actually it's possible it's not
the correct 값.
but actually it's possible it's not the correct
value.
원문 의미: 하지만 in practice, the authors see
that it
But in practice, the authors see that it
원문 의미: tends to improve metrics like BLEU,
tends to improve metrics like BLEU,
원문 의미: which is a proxy metric for
translation tasks.
which is a proxy metric for translation tasks.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, I think this method is
pretty general for NLP.
So yeah, I think this method is pretty general
for NLP.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, it's a good one to know.
So yeah, it's a good one to know.
원문 의미: 그리고 with that, I think there's
about 20-ish minutes left.
And with that, I think there's about 20-ish
minutes left.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, Shervine is ~할 예정입니다 walk
you
So yeah, Shervine is going to walk you
through an 엔드투엔드 예시.
through an end-to-end example.
원문 의미: 그리고 with that, you—
And with that, you--
yeah, Oh, u?
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess here 생각할 수 있습니다 of this
as, I guess, some quantity.
So I guess here you can think of this as, I
guess, some quantity.
원문 의미: It's not defined, so some quantity.
It's not defined, so some quantity.
원문 의미: 그리고 the delta is like one hot, if
you want, something
And the delta is like one hot, if you want,
something
like this.
원문 의미: It can also be a constant.
It can also be a constant.
Yeah, yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 question is, is there a
relation
So question is, is there a relation
원문 의미: with explore and exploit?
with explore and exploit?
원문 의미: It's an interesting one.
It's an interesting one.
원문 의미: 그래서 why would 소프트맥스 give it for
free, by the way?
So why would softmax give it for free, by the
way?
원문 의미: Right, but I guess it would still—
Right, but I guess it would still--
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess at the end of the day,
what you're
so I guess at the end of the day, what you're
원문 의미: trying to do is to compare your
prediction with respect
trying to do is to compare your prediction with
respect
to the label.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess the question here is,
do you
So I guess the question here is, do you
원문 의미: want to compare with 1, 0, 0, 0, or
do you
want to compare with 1, 0, 0, 0, or do you
원문 의미: want to compare with something that
is not 1, 0, 0, 0.
want to compare with something that is not 1, 0,
0, 0.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess 소프트맥스 does not allow
you to do that.
So I guess softmax does not allow you to do
that.
Exactly, yes.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm not sure if this was super
clear,
So I'm not sure if this was super clear,
원문 의미: 하지만 this is actually the label.
but this is actually the label.
원문 의미: 그래서 what you're trying to predict
is not 1, 0, 0.
So what you're trying to predict is not 1, 0, 0.
원문 의미: 하지만 we change the label in a way
that makes the 모델,
But we change the label in a way that makes the
model,
원문 의미: I guess, predict something that is
less sure, I guess.
I guess, predict something that is less sure, I
guess.
Cool, thanks.
원문 의미: 그리고 with that, yeah, Shervine.
And with that, yeah, Shervine.
OK, great.
원문 의미: Thank you, Afshine.
Thank you, Afshine.
그리고 yes, so 우리가 보았습니다 basically how the
트랜스포머 worked.
And yes, so we saw basically how the transformer
worked.
원문 의미: 그리고 now we're ~할 예정입니다 piece it all
together
And now we're going to piece it all together
원문 의미: with the one specific 예시.
with the one specific example.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's take our favorite 예시
again.
So let's take our favorite example again.
원문 의미: 그래서 a cute teddy bear is reading.
So a cute teddy bear is reading.
원문 의미: 그리고 then we'll go all together
through each step.
And then we'll go all together through each
step.
원문 의미: 그래서 first we start with 토큰화.
So first we start with tokenization.
원문 의미: 그래서 as we said, we can use any
arbitrary decomposition
So as we said, we can use any arbitrary
decomposition
원문 의미: to decompose this into 토큰.
to decompose this into tokens.
원문 의미: 그리고 then as someone mentioned, you
And then as someone mentioned, you
원문 의미: need to have some way to indicate
the start and the end
need to have some way to indicate the start and
the end
of a 시퀀스.
of a sequence.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, this is done with
the BOS and EOS 토큰.
So typically, this is done with the BOS and EOS
tokens.
그래서 you add them.
So you add them.
원문 의미: 그래서 now let's focus on the
composition
So now let's focus on the composition
원문 의미: of each 토큰 representation.
of each token representation.
그래서 you have its 임베딩.
So you have its embedding.
원문 의미: That is learned.
That is learned.
원문 의미: 그리고 as Afshine mentioned, in order
And as Afshine mentioned, in order
원문 의미: to have an idea of what is the
position of the words
to have an idea of what is the position of the
words
원문 의미: or the 토큰, I should say as 일부 시퀀스,
or the token, I should say as part of the
sequence,
원문 의미: you have some added information
that
you have some added information that
원문 의미: is in the form of a position 임베딩.
is in the form of a position embedding.
원문 의미: 그리고 here, the original paper uses
the convention
And here, the original paper uses the convention
원문 의미: of some sines and cosines that it
adds additively
of some sines and cosines that it adds
additively
원문 의미: to the representation.
to the representation.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's like an element-wise
addition.
So it's like an element-wise addition.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 now you have a position-aware
임베딩 for your 토큰.
So now you have a position-aware embedding for
your token.
그리고 you repeat that 각각에 대해 of your 토큰.
And you repeat that for each of your tokens.
그래서 now 여러분이 볼 수 있습니다 모든se 임베딩
So now you can see all of these embeddings
원문 의미: in the format of a 행렬, which is of
size d 모델, which
in the format of a matrix, which is of size d
model, which
원문 의미: is the size of your 임베딩.
is the size of your embeddings.
원문 의미: 그리고 then the other 차원 is the length
And then the other dimension is the length
원문 의미: of the 시퀀스, so typically n.
of the sequence, so typically n.
그래서 all 말이 됩니다 so far?
So all make sense so far?
원문 의미: Any questions on the 입력s?
Any questions on the inputs?
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 now we will send this
representation
So now we will send this representation
through the 인코더.
through the encoder.
원문 의미: 그래서 as Afshine said, you have this
concept of 셀프 어텐션.
So as Afshine said, you have this concept of
self-attention.
그리고 the way you perform 셀프 어텐션
And the way you perform self-attention
원문 의미: is that you take this 입력 and
project it on three spaces.
is that you take this input and project it on
three spaces.
원문 의미: 그래서 you project it to the space Wq,
you get 쿼리들.
So you project it to the space Wq, you get
queries.
원문 의미: You project the same 임베딩 in the
space Wk, you get 키.
You project the same embeddings in the space Wk,
you get keys.
원문 의미: 그리고 you do the same for 값, you get
your 값.
And you do the same for values, you get your
values.
원문 의미: 그리고 then Wq, Wk, and Wv are learned
by the 모델.
And then Wq, Wk, and Wv are learned by the
model.
원문 의미: They are basically projection 행렬들.
They are basically projection matrices.
그래서 far, so good?
So far, so good?
원문 의미: 그래서 now with all of that in mind,
you
So now with all of that in mind, you
원문 의미: can apply the formula that Afshine
mentioned,
can apply the formula that Afshine mentioned,
원문 의미: that is the 셀프 어텐션 formula,
that is the self-attention formula,
원문 의미: which is 소프트맥스 of Qk transpose over
square root of dk
which is softmax of Qk transpose over square
root of dk
원문 의미: times v, which gives you another 행렬
중에서 all of this.
times v, which gives you another matrix out of
all of this.
원문 의미: 이제 let's pause for a second and
look
Now let's pause for a second and look
원문 의미: at how this computation is done in
practice
at how this computation is done in practice
원문 의미: 그리고 what every step means.
and what every step means.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's look at Q. When you
compute Q,
So let's look at Q. When you compute Q,
원문 의미: basically you project your 임베딩 into
that space.
basically you project your embeddings into that
space.
원문 의미: What do you obtain?
What do you obtain?
원문 의미: You obtain a 행렬 where each row
represents a given 쿼리.
You obtain a matrix where each row represents a
given query.
원문 의미: When you say k transpose, it's
basically
When you say k transpose, it's basically
원문 의미: the same 행렬, but transposed, where
the same matrix, but transposed, where
원문 의미: each column represents the 키
representation of each 토큰.
each column represents the key representation of
each token.
원문 의미: 이제 let's mix them together with the
행렬 multiplication.
Now let's mix them together with the matrix
multiplication.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you multiply each of them,
So when you multiply each of them,
원문 의미: you see that each row represents
the projection
you see that each row represents the projection
원문 의미: of the 쿼리 over each 키, such that
when you take the 행렬
of the query over each key, such that when you
take the matrix
원문 의미: multiplication and get the 소프트맥스 of
all of this,
multiplication and get the softmax of all of
this,
you get a 확률분포
you get a probability distribution
원문 의미: of the projection of the 쿼리 over 키
각각에 대해 쿼리.
of the projection of the query over keys for
each query.
원문 의미: Each line will have this.
Each line will have this.
원문 의미: 그리고 I don't know if anyone asked
the question regarding why do we
And I don't know if anyone asked the question
regarding why do we
원문 의미: scale by square root of dk?
scale by square root of dk?
원문 의미: 그래서 it could be dq 역시 because 행렬
multiplication,
So it could be dq as well because matrix
원문 의미: like the dot product here, enforces
like the dot product here, enforces
원문 의미: the fact that dq equals dk.
the fact that dq equals dk.
원문 의미: 그리고 basically, what you see is that
these dot products has
And basically, what you see is that these dot
products has
원문 의미: the 차원 of 키 and 쿼리들 grows,
the dimension of key and queries grows,
원문 의미: it will tend to grow 역시.
it will tend to grow as well.
그래서 여러분은 normalize these dot products.
So you want to normalize these dot products.
원문 의미: 그리고 this is why you divide by
square root
And this is why you divide by square root
of the 차원 of 키.
of the dimension of keys.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 then now you have your 소프트맥스 of
모든se,
And then now you have your softmax of all of
these,
원문 의미: 그리고 then you multiply it with the
행렬
and then you multiply it with the matrix
원문 의미: v. And this is Afshine explained as
having the 쿼리 projected
v. And this is Afshine explained as having the
query projected
원문 의미: on the space of 키, and then
multiplied
on the space of keys, and then multiplied
원문 의미: by the corresponding 값.
by the corresponding value.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 값 is the representation
So the value is the representation
원문 의미: of the corresponding 키 that we
project on.
of the corresponding key that we project on.
그래서 you end up with a 가중치ed sum of 값 각각에
대해 쿼리.
So you end up with a weighted sum of values for
each query.
OK, great.
원문 의미: Does that 말이 됩니다 so far?
Does that make sense so far?
좋습니다, 훌륭합니다.
OK, awesome.
원문 의미: 그리고 someone asked, what is the 멀티헤드
stuff?
And someone asked, what is the multi-head stuff?
원문 의미: 그래서 you're right, it's not just
single one, one time
So you're right, it's not just single one, one
time
원문 의미: that it's done.
that it's done.
원문 의미: It's actually done each times.
It's actually done each times.
원문 의미: 그리고 what you obtain is, like, all
of that is done in parallel.
And what you obtain is, like, all of that is
done in parallel.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the end, you obtain h such
행렬들.
And at the end, you obtain h such matrices.
원문 의미: 그리고 you concatenate them with
respect to the columns.
And you concatenate them with respect to the
columns.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the end of this, you have
another projection 행렬
And at the end of this, you have another
projection matrix
원문 의미: that you call Wo that will project
모든se back
that you call Wo that will project all of these
back
원문 의미: to the original 차원 of 임베딩.
to the original dimension of embeddings.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's a way for the network to
basically have
So it's a way for the network to basically have
원문 의미: a 차원-invariant way—
a dimension-invariant way--
원문 의미: bless you— to go from the original
차원
bless you-- to go from the original dimension
원문 의미: back to the original one.
back to the original one.
질문 있나요?
Any questions?
Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 the question is regarding h.
So the question is regarding h.
원문 의미: Is it possible to get the same
result each time?
Is it possible to get the same result each time?
원문 의미: 그리고 if so, concatenate the same
thing, will it be helpful?
And if so, concatenate the same thing, will it
be helpful?
원문 의미: Did I get the question right?
Did I get the question right?
원문 의미: 그래서 what makes it different?
So what makes it different?
그래서 it's the magic of 경사하강법.
So it's the magic of gradient descent.
원문 의미: 그래서 the network has an objective
function at the end.
So the network has an objective function at the
end.
원문 의미: It has degrees of freedom.
It has degrees of freedom.
원문 의미: Its incentive is to build a
representation that will be
Its incentive is to build a representation that
will be
원문 의미: helpful to learn the next word.
helpful to learn the next word.
원문 의미: 그래서 it doesn't have an incentive to
copy the same thing
So it doesn't have an incentive to copy the same
thing
원문 의미: or do the same mechanism.
or do the same mechanism.
원문 의미: 그리고 this is why in practice you see
the 모델 converge
And this is why in practice you see the model
converge
원문 의미: towards building different
representations that it can then
towards building different representations that
it can then
원문 의미: concatenate and then project into
something useful.
concatenate and then project into something
useful.
원문 의미: 그래서 what makes it such that you
don't have the same thing?
So what makes it such that you don't have the
same thing?
Nothing.
원문 의미: Like, you don't have any
cons학습하다ts.
Like, you don't have any constraints.
원문 의미: 하지만 the nature of the learning that
you let the 모델 have
But the nature of the learning that you let the
model have
원문 의미: makes it do so in practice.
makes it do so in practice.
다른 질문 있나요?
Any other questions?
원문 의미: 그리고 that is a great question.
And that is a great question.
원문 의미: I mean, typically 경사하강법 does
wonders.
I mean, typically gradient descent does wonders.
OK great.
원문 의미: 그래서 now that we have gone through
the 셀프 어텐션 layer,
So now that we have gone through the
self-attention layer,
원문 의미: you have another component that is
the FFN.
you have another component that is the FFN.
원문 의미: 그리고 I think there was a question
just here regarding
And I think there was a question just here
regarding
원문 의미: how to choose the 차원 of the hidden
layer
how to choose the dimension of the hidden layer
원문 의미: with respect to the 입력 and 출력s.
with respect to the input and outputs.
원문 의미: 그래서 when Afshine mentioned
Word2vec,
So when Afshine mentioned Word2vec,
원문 의미: typically you have a smaller 차원
typically you have a smaller dimension
than the 입력 and 출력.
than the input and output.
원문 의미: 하지만 here, actually, the hidden
layer
But here, actually, the hidden layer
원문 의미: is of a bigger 차원 than 입력 and 출력.
is of a bigger dimension than input and output.
원문 의미: 그리고 the rationale for that is that
you
And the rationale for that is that you
원문 의미: want to have enough degrees of
freedom for the 모델 to learn
want to have enough degrees of freedom for the
model to learn
원문 의미: useful representations.
useful representations.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's a way to complexify the
features that you learn.
So it's a way to complexify the features that
you learn.
원문 의미: And, yeah [INAUDIBLE].
And, yeah [INAUDIBLE].
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 you don't have just one 인코더
module.
And you don't have just one encoder module.
원문 의미: You have actually n of them, big N
in the original paper.
You have actually n of them, big N in the
original paper.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the end of all of this, you
And at the end of all of this, you
원문 의미: have an encoded 문맥-aware set of
임베딩.
have an encoded context-aware set of embeddings.
원문 의미: 그리고 then each of these setups
encoded
And then each of these setups encoded
원문 의미: 임베딩 will be those that will be fed
to the n 디코더s.
embeddings will be those that will be fed to the
n decoders.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have like a stacked
succession of n 인코더s.
So you have like a stacked succession of n
encoders.
원문 의미: You have a stacked succession of n
디코더s.
You have a stacked succession of n decoders.
원문 의미: 그리고 the last representation of the
인코더
And the last representation of the encoder
원문 의미: is what you will feed to the
cross-어텐션 of each 디코더.
is what you will feed to the cross-attention of
each decoder.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, we're ~할 예정입니다 see that
more in detail.
So yeah, we're going to see that more in detail.
원문 의미: 그래서 how do we even start the
decoding process?
So how do we even start the decoding process?
원문 의미: 그래서 you start with the BOS 토큰.
So you start with the BOS token.
원문 의미: Basically saying to the 모델, hey, we
Basically saying to the model, hey, we
원문 의미: need to predict the next word,
let's start.
need to predict the next word, let's start.
원문 의미: 그래서 what happens to the BOS 토큰 at
the very beginning?
So what happens to the BOS token at the very
beginning?
원문 의미: 그래서 you feed it to the 디코더.
So you feed it to the decoder.
원문 의미: 그리고 then similarly as before for
the 인코더,
And then similarly as before for the encoder,
원문 의미: you have a 셀프 어텐션 layer.
you have a self-attention layer.
원문 의미: 그리고 as Afshine mentioned, the 셀프
어텐션 layer is causal.
And as Afshine mentioned, the self-attention
layer is causal.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 어텐션 will be done on the
same 토큰
So the attention will be done on the same token
원문 의미: 그리고 the 토큰 that precede it.
and the tokens that precede it.
원문 의미: 그래서 on this first BOS 토큰, you don't
see a difference,
So on this first BOS token, you don't see a
difference,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 it will just attend to itself.
because it will just attend to itself.
하지만 when you have other 토큰 that 여러분은
decode,
But when you have other tokens that you want to
원문 의미: you will have this difference in
where you
you will have this difference in where you
원문 의미: attend with respect to 디코더.
attend with respect to decoder.
원문 의미: OK, great, goes through the 셀프 어텐션
layer.
OK, great, goes through the self-attention
원문 의미: 그리고 then you have what I mentioned
And then you have what I mentioned
원문 의미: to be the cross-어텐션 that takes as 키
and 값
to be the cross-attention that takes as keys and
values
원문 의미: these encoded 임베딩 as 입력s.
these encoded embeddings as inputs.
원문 의미: 그리고 then the 쿼리들 are those that
come out
And then the queries are those that come out
of the 셀프 어텐션 layer.
of the self-attention layer.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 then once you do this
cross-어텐션,
And then once you do this cross-attention,
원문 의미: you have, just like in the 인코더,
you have, just like in the encoder,
원문 의미: an FFN component that makes the
representation richer.
an FFN component that makes the representation
richer.
원문 의미: Was there a question there?
Was there a question there?
No.
원문 의미: 그리고 then at the very end, so you do
all of that n times.
And then at the very end, so you do all of that
n times.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the very end of the decoding
process,
And at the very end of the decoding process,
원문 의미: you have a linear projection and a
소프트맥스 layer
you have a linear projection and a softmax layer
원문 의미: to turn the prediction of the next
word
to turn the prediction of the next word
원문 의미: into a 확률분포 over the vocabulary.
into a probability distribution over the
vocabulary.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 우리가 보았습니다 how to do that for
the next word here.
So we saw how to do that for the next word here.
원문 의미: 그리고 basically you do that again and
again.
And basically you do that again and again.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have found your next 토큰,
So you have found your next token,
원문 의미: which is like a one-hot basically
which is like a one-hot basically
원문 의미: encoding of what you want.
encoding of what you want.
원문 의미: 그리고 then you take that 임베딩 and then
put it back
And then you take that embedding and then put it
back
원문 의미: in the 디코더 and continue this
process.
in the decoder and continue this process.
원문 의미: 그리고 when do you stop?
And when do you stop?
원문 의미: It's a question for you all.
It's a question for you all.
원문 의미: When you hit the EOS 토큰.
When you hit the EOS token.
원문 의미: Yeah, yeah exactly.
Yeah, yeah exactly.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 with this process, it's
basically
And with this process, it's basically
원문 의미: how the authors of this original
landmark paper
how the authors of this original landmark paper
did 기계번역.
did machine translation.
원문 의미: 그래서 this is typically the use case
that was presented.
So this is typically the use case that was
presented.
질문 있나요?
Any questions?
좋습니다, 훌륭합니다.
OK, awesome.
원문 의미: 그리고 with that, thank you for your
어텐션.
And with that, thank you for your attention.
[박수]
[APPLAUSE]